<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The anatomie of conscience Or a threefold reuelation of those three most secret bookes: 1. The booke of Gods prescience. 2. The booke of mans conscience. 3. The booke of life. In a sermon preached at the generall assises holden at Derby, in Lent last. 1623. By Immanuel Bourne ...</title>
            <author>Bourne, Immanuel, 1590-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106813</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842523</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842523</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1091:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The anatomie of conscience Or a threefold reuelation of those three most secret bookes: 1. The booke of Gods prescience. 2. The booke of mans conscience. 3. The booke of life. In a sermon preached at the generall assises holden at Derby, in Lent last. 1623. By Immanuel Bourne ...</title>
                  <author>Bourne, Immanuel, 1590-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. E[ld] and M. F[lesher] for Nathaniel Butter, and are to be sold at his shop neere S. Austins Gate, at the signe of the Pyde Bull,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The words "1. The booke of God prescience. .. 3. The booke of life." are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  t17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7186:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANATOMIE OF CONSCIENCE. <hi>OR</hi> A THREEFOLD REVELA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe three moſt ſecret Bookes:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Booke of Gods Preſcience.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Booke of Mans Conſcience.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The Booke of Life.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached at the generall Aſsiſes holden at <hi>Derby,</hi> in <hi>Lent</hi> laſt. 1623.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Immanuel Bourne</hi> Maſter of Arts and Parſon of <hi>Aſhouer</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 24.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And herein doe I exerciſe my ſelfe, to haue alwayes a Conſcience voyd of offence towards God and towards men.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. E.</hi> and <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Gate, at the Signe of <hi>the Pyde Bull.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7186:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7186:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND RIGHT REVEREND Father in God, <hi>Iohn</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne,</hi> Lord Keeper of the great Seale; And one of his Maieſties moſt Honorable Priuie COVNCELL: The true Honour of a good Conſcience in the Church Militant, and the reward of true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Church Triumphant.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O many are the Bills of Complaint <hi>(Right Honorable)</hi> of thoſe who are dayly petitioners vnto your Lordſhip, for your graue and Conſcionable Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in matters of <hi>Equity,</hi> that there needeth no further teſtimonie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Conſciences of all thoſe, who mourne for the iniquities of the <hi>Times:</hi> That eyther <hi>Conſcience</hi> is fled already from <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>Heauen,</hi> (as it was long ſince complained of <hi>Iuſtice</hi>) or elſe the moſt of men are euen now <hi>plotting</hi> to baniſh her out of the world; exerciſing themſelues (contrary to the practice of S. <hi>Paul</hi>) to haue alwayes their <hi>Conſciences</hi> not voyd, but full of offences both towards God and towards men. But praiſed be the Lord of mercy, who hath ſhewed kindneſſe towards his Seruants; and placed your <hi>Honor</hi> as the <hi>Lord-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in theſe perillous times of her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.
<pb facs="tcp:7186:3"/> Amongst diuers others whoſe hearts-deſire is bent, to manifeſt their thankefulneſſe to God for his Grace already ſhewed; and to pray for a dayly encreaſe of happineſſe vnto your Lordſhip: I am emboldened to ſend this <hi>Anatomie of Conſcience,</hi> to be reuiued with the warmth of your Honorable fauour in this cold and frozen Age of the world. It was at firſt preached before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and worthy <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> for the County of <hi>Derby;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sir Henry Hobart, Sir Edward Bromely.</note> the memory of whoſe free Approbation (with the reſt of that worthy Auditory,) hath ſince emboldened mee to caſt an eie ouer it once againe; and that I might ſatisfie the deſire of ſome few, to publiſh it for the benefit of many. And now if it pleaſe your Lordſhip to vouchſafe vnto it a ſhadow of <hi>Protection;</hi> I ſhall not ceaſe to pray (in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, as I doe in publike,) That the Lord will ſo guard you with his glorious <hi>Angels;</hi> &amp; guide you by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his gracious <hi>Spirit;</hi> That all your <hi>Counſels,</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> may tend to the Glory of his holy <hi>Name,</hi> the <hi>Reliefe</hi> and <hi>Comfort</hi> of the <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> the good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> And thus commending you to the <hi>ſafe Tuition</hi> of the great <hi>Lord-Keeper</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>Iuly <hi>14. 1623.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt humble and dutifull Chaplaine IMMANVEL BOVRNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7186:3"/>
            <head>THE ANATOMIE OF CONSCIENCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVELATION 20.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And the Bookes were opened, and another booke was ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which is the Booke of Life.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <label>Preface.</label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Baſil</hi> the great (who was <hi>Magni nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis in Eccleſia,</hi> of great account in the Church of God) expounding thoſe words of the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> 1.17. <hi>Diſcite benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi> Learne to doe well; hee giueth this excellent admonition, worthy to bee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of euery Chriſtian, <hi>Habete in oculis terribilem judicii diem tanquam Pedagogum,</hi> Haue alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eies that terrible day of Iudgment as a Pedagogue or Schoolemaſter, not onely to inſtruct, but by an awfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to keepe you in well doing. And if that great and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſiſes (when wee muſt all appeare before the tribunall Seat of Chriſt) be a meditation fitting for euery Chriſtian, and that at all times, and in all our actions; (as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> intimates) then certainly it muſt needs be <hi>verbum in tempore,</hi> a word not vnfitting for the time and ſeaſon, to ſpeake of iudgment, and the preparation to iudgment, at a time of iudgment; to ſpeake of that generall, in this particular; in this preſent, of that for to come. And rather, becauſe there is an Analogie, a reſemblance, a ſimilitude betweene them: For the Spirit of God (to declare that loue of God to man) deſcribing in ſacred Scriptures the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7186:4"/> things of God oftentimes deſcends to mans capacity; and as in other ſo in this portion of Scripture: For being to ſhew <hi>Iohn</hi> the day of Iudgment, and the manner of Chriſts preparation, hee takes a ſimilitude from earthly <hi>Iudges,</hi> whoſe place of iudgment is commonly a <hi>Throne</hi> or Seat made more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous then the reſt, ſet forth in ſtate conuenient for ſo high an <hi>Action;</hi> vpon which the Iudge aſcendeth, being clothed with <hi>Roabes</hi> and ornaments of iuſtice, (wiſely ordained by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity) as emblems of that grauity, ſincerity, and maieſtie of a Iudge, the very ſight of whom, is and ſhould bee both a ioy and comfort to the innocent; and a feare and terrour to the nocent: the Iudge being ſet with his <hi>Aſſiſtants,</hi> and in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, next are the Priſoners brought vnto the Barre: and then the books are opened, examination taken, and euidence giuen; and laſt of all, the ſentence is pronounced to acquit the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and condemne the guilty. This is the forme of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iudgment. And in a manner not much vnlike to this, (if you caſt your eyes vpon this viſion) you may find the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings ſhall bee in that laſt and generall Aſſiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The diuiſion of the Viſion.</label> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> beheld a <hi>Throne,</hi> moſt white and pure (in which no ſpot of foule iniuſtice could be ſeene) and him that ſat thereon (euen Chriſt, that righteous Iudge, both God and man) from whoſe maieſticke face <hi>The earth and heauen did flye away,</hi> as the Spirit ſpeakes in the firſt part of the Viſion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Next this appeared the Priſoners, <hi>The dead both ſmall and great;</hi> all people from all quarters, none excepted; and theſe all <hi>Did ſtand before God,</hi> as ready to receiue their tryall. So it followeth in the immediate words before my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the Iudge proceeds to examination of euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and euery action; and this in the words that I haue read: <hi>The Bookes were opened, and another booke was opened which is the Booke of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, examination being taken, and euidence giuen, the Sentence is pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>unced accordingly, this you may ſee in the words adioyning: <hi>And the Dead were iudged of thoſe things which were written in the Bookes, according to their workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I firſt caſt mine eyes vpon this Viſion, I ſaw it was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7186:4"/> not vnfitting for this time: But is too much to bee compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended within a regular houre (as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> calleth it) and therefore reſolued onely on the words of my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Bookes were opened, and another booke was opened, which is the Booke of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the preparation vnto the Sentence, and indeed the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> rule and ſquare of that moſt righteous iudgment; a patterne moſt fit for imitation, and moſt profitable to bee remembred, to keepe vs iuſt and right in all our actions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>The Bookes were opened.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Explication.</label> Almighty God in Scripture is ſaid to haue Books, not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but <hi>per</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by that vſuall metaphor in which the Scripture ſpeakes to mens capacity, that men might vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the will of God: ſo in the former, and ſo in this part of the Viſion; for God needs not bookes to regiſter mens names or actions, hee is infinite in knowledge, and of endleſſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory: knowne vnto God are all his workes (and ſo all both words and workes of men) from the foundation of the world. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.18.</p>
            <p>But thus the Viſion was to ſhew by this the matter that ſhall then bee put in execution: the bookes ſhall then bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is, euery man and euery worke ſhall then be tryed, and as euidence is giuen and actions found, ſo ſhall the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he pronounced.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Diuiſion of the Text.</label> There are diuers kinds of Bookes in Scripture mentioned, ſome giuen to God and ſome to man: I onely caſt my eies vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Text. And to let paſſe variety of opinions, and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Diuines about theſe bookes, I finde, as moſt accord, theſe bookes are three.<note place="margin">Perkinſius in ſymbol. Seb. Mey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r in Apocalyp. Inchino de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſsim.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, <hi>Liber praeſcientiae,</hi> the Booke of Gods eternall preſcience or fore-knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, <hi>Liber conſcientiae,</hi> the booke of euery mans par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular conſcience. Both theſe are vnderſtood, and not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but of theſe, Diuines expound thoſe former words, <hi>The bookes were opened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third and laſt is, <hi>Liber vitae,</hi> the booke of life: and this is named in the words that follow: <hi>And another booke was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7186:5"/> opened, which is the Booke of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>The Booke of Gods preſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence opened.</label> Of theſe in order, by aſſiſtance of Gods gracious Spirit, your Chriſtian patience, and the times permiſſion. And firſt of the firſt of theſe moſt ſecret Bookes, The booke of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall preſcience, and foreknowledge. This ſhall be opened at that great Aſſiſes: For as the <hi>Lord is a God of knowledge,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.3. knowing euery <hi>word in our tongues,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.6. hauing all things <hi>written</hi> before-hand in his <hi>Booke: ver.</hi> 16. <hi>And diſcerning the hearts of the Children of men: Prou.</hi> 15.11. So will hee manifeſt this knowledge at that day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.26.</note> 
               <hi>There is nothing hid that ſhall not be reuealed, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſecret ſhall not be brought to light. Luc.</hi> 12.2. God will bring euery work vnto iudgment with euery ſecret thing, whether it be good or euill.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>Eccles</hi> 12.14. <hi>Iudg nothing before the time</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) vntill the Lord come, who will bring to light the hidden things of darkeneſſe, and make manifeſt the counſels o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the heart.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.<hi>5. Aderit dies illa, in qua omnia facta hominis quaſi in quadam tabula picta demonſtrabuntur;</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Hieronym. Epiſtol. ad Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Baſil Tract. de virginitat.</note> (as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſpeakes) That day ſhall come, in which all the deeds of men ſhall bee made plaine, as it were in painted tables. Yea, not onely the actions, but the way and meanes which euery one hath vſed in committing wickedneſſe, as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> teſtifieth: to whom S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>5.</hi> in epiſt. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Simil. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and diuers other of the ancient Fathers agree. But how ſhall this bee, may ſome man demand? I anſwer. Euen as in euery houſe or chamber the ayre is full of ſands or moats, which cannot be diſcerned vntill the Sunne beames make the ayre ſeeme light, and then theſe <hi>Atomi,</hi> theſe moats are ſeene in great abundance: Euen ſo thoſe ſecret ſinnes which now lye hidden within the chambers of mens hearts, when as the Sunne of righteouſneſſe ſhall lighten euery corner, ſhall then be manifeſt vnto the eies of all. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Simil. </seg>2</label> Or, as in winter when the earth is couered with the ſnow, the fowleſt bogs and moſt vnwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome places ſeeme faire and white as doe the beſt, but when the Sunne once comes and melts the ſnow, then is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſeene, and that place preſently auoided, which before at vnawares a man with danger of his life might ſoone haue fallen into: So, when the heauens ſhall bee on fire, and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7186:5"/> elements ſhall melt with feruent heat, and Chriſt the Iudge of all diſſolue the Snow, that is, vnmaske the fowleſt face of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall hypocriſie; then ſhall the vgly countenance of ſinne be ſhewne, and thoſe polluted ſoules (which like deformed bodies, couered with gay apparell) haue walked in ſilken roabes of ſeeming righteouſneſſe, ſtand naked vnto all behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, abhorred of God, and men, and Angels, for their blacke impieties.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vſe.</label> Tremble then yee Hypocrites, who make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue yee are holy, iuſt, and good, while horrid wickedneſſe is guilded ouer with colours of deceit, who thinke to cozen God with faire pretences, as yee can doe men. But yee are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, God knoweth your ſecrets now, and then ſhall make them manifeſt vnto the world. Then is a time of tryall, when the ſiluer ſhall be ſeuered from the droſſe, and the wheat win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed from the chaffe, for his fanne is in his hand, and hee will throughly purge his floore, and gather his wheat into his Garner, but burne vp the chaffe with vnquenchable fire. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12. Hieruſalem ſhall then be ſearched, and that with lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne and candle-light. <hi>Zephan.</hi> 1. that is,<note place="margin">Zephan. 1.12. <hi>Bern Serm</hi> 55. <hi>in Cantic.</hi>
               </note> the Saints them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſhall be enquired into (as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> interprets it.) And <hi>Quid tutum in Babylone, ſi Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manet ſcrutinium?</hi> (ſaith the ſame Father) What ſhall become of Babylon, the prophane and wicked world; if Hieruſalem, the holy City, ſhall be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? <hi>Quid facient tabulae, quando tremunt columnae?</hi> (as ſpeakes S. <hi>Gregory</hi>) What ſhall the ſlender Tables doe, when the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the houſe doe quake and tremble? If the greene tree be curſed for bearing onely leaues without good fruit,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.19.</note> what ſhall bee done vnto the dry, which bringeth not forth ſo much as leaues of good profeſſion, hauing neither ſhew nor ſubſtance of deuotion in them? Certainly confuſion, ſhame, and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſhall bee their portion, helliſh horror ſhall take hold vpon them, when God ſhall open the Booke of his preſcience, and make them a gazing ſtocke to Angells, men, and Deuills.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Application.</label> Wherefore if any ſuch be preſent, let my counſell be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto you, breake off your ſinnes by righteouſneſſe, and your iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poore,<note place="margin">Daniel 4.12.</note> if ſo be there
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7186:6"/> may bee a healing of your tranquility; if not, you haue heard already what ſhall then betide you, when the Bookes are opened.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vſe 2.</label> But as for you yee Sons of righteouſneſſe, whoſe hearts are vpright towards your God, lift vp your heads, for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth nigh. <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.28. <hi>Bleſſed are yee for your iniquities are forgiuen, and ſinnes are couered. Pſal.</hi> 32.1.2. <hi>The Lord will blot out your tranſgreſſions and remember your ſinnes no more. Eſay</hi> 43.25. But for your righteouſneſſe that ſhall bee had in euerlaſting memory, your workes of piety, and works of pitty ſhall not be forgotten.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.36. Though other men vniuſtly cenſure you, it is God that ſeeth in ſecret, and will reward you openly: your zeale for truth and righteouſneſſe are in his preſence:<note place="margin">Act. 10.4.</note> your <hi>prayers and almes-deeds</hi> are gone to heauen before you: your ſighs, and ſobs, and <hi>teares</hi> in ſecret, he <hi>putteth into his bottle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> and all theſe things are <hi>noted in his Booke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reioyce therefore in the Lord alwaies, and againe I ſay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, for it is for your good that the Bookes are opened. And thus you haue ſeene the firſt booke, the booke of Gods eternal preſcience and foreknowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <label>2 The Booke of Conſcience o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</label> The ſecond followeth, and this is <hi>Liber Conſcientiae,</hi> The Booke of euery mans particular Conſcience, for this alſo ſhall be opened at that laſt day of reckoning (as the Maſter of the Sentences affirmes in his fourth booke and forty three Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Now, <hi>Conſcientia dicitur cum alio ſcientiae</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi>) Conſcience is ſaid to bee knowledge with another:<note place="margin">Aquinas prim. par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sum qu. <hi>79.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tic. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</hi>
               </note> and well it may, becauſe God and conſcience beare witneſſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Or, <hi>Conſcience</hi> is <hi>Cordis ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ientia,</hi> the ſcience or knowledg <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of the <hi>heart,</hi> becauſe the heart knoweth both it ſelfe and other things.<note place="margin">Hugo de anima li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> When it knoweth other things, it is called <hi>ſcience;</hi> and when it knoweth it ſelfe, it is called <hi>conſcience,</hi> (as <hi>Hugo, de anima</hi> obſerues) Therefore the Scripture calleth Conſcience the Heart, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.20. and rightly it may in this reſpect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> reflects vpon the <hi>Heart,</hi> being enlightned by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the <hi>vnderſtanding;</hi> and hence it is, <hi>Concludens ſcientia,</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding ſcience (as the Schoolemen ſpeake) arguing out of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7186:6"/> principles, from whence it either acquitteth or condemneth vs in all our actions. I cannot ſtand to ſhew you at large the diuers opinions of the Schooles, and other Diuines concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Booke of Conſcience. I will as briefly as I can giue you a touch of ſome few, that you may the better conceiue what Conſcience is. <note place="margin">Ori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en lib. <hi>2.</hi> in Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> hee thought that Conſcience was euery mans particular <hi>Angell,</hi> a good conſcience a good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, and a bad conſcience an euill Angell: but this conceit was weake without proofe or approbation. Some thinke this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Sparke</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to be <hi>Habitus animae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Relicta rationis ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lia. Aquinas <hi>1.</hi> par. Sum. qu. <hi>79.</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. <hi>12.</hi> &amp; <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> A habit of the Soule: to which <hi>Aquinas</hi> bendeth in the firſt part of his Summes, Queſtion the ſeuenty nine, Article the twelfth: But in the thirteenth Article he concludeth, that it properly is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Actus animae,</hi> An acte of the Soule, reflecting vpon it ſelfe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and by application of the vnderſtanding, iudging what is good and what is evill. Some haue deemed it to bee <hi>Res mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A thing that's mixt of both, partly a Habit, and partly an Act: ſo <hi>Durandus</hi> and other Schoolemen.</p>
            <p>Some later Diuines doe thinke it to be an office or function of the Soule, ſet as an <hi>Arbitrator,</hi> not onely to examine,<note place="margin">Humes. Perkinſ.</note> but to giue euidence and iudge of particular actions between God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and man. For as that office of the ſoule, by which a man doth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> thinke or imagine, is called the <hi>minde;</hi> and that, by which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a man diſcuſſeth and diſcerneth things conceiued, is called the <hi>reaſon</hi> or <hi>iudgment;</hi> and that wherby the things apprehended <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and diſcuſſed, are preſerued and kept, is called the <hi>memory;</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo, that function or office of the ſoule, wherby a man (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> enquiry) is certified, that the things which hee hath done are good or euill, is called Conſcience. And this office of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the moſt affirm to be a diuine facultie or power in the ſoule, working vpon it ſelfe by reflection. For thus the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, by cooperation and help of other faculties in the ſoule, produceth ſeuerall effects, according to the ſeuerall ſubiects or actions, about which it is conuerſant, declaring to the Soule what is the ſtate and condition of it, and by this means it is affected either with ioy or griefe, with feare or boldneſſe, when it thinks on God the maker, who knoweth the ſoule
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7186:7"/> and Conſcience, as the Conſcience knoweth it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And thus is Conſcience an excellent part of the Image of God in man: for as God looking into himſelfe from all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſeeth himſelfe, and begetteth his Sonne, the expreſſe image of his Father; euen ſo the Soule of man which is diuine, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon it ſelfe, ſeeth and beholdeth it ſelfe, with the ſtate and condition thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> But how can this be, may ſome man demand?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> I anſwer. Euen as in a looking-glaſſe a man ſeeth his owne face by reflection, and diſcerneth the beauty or deformity of that, &amp; the eye ſeeth it ſelfe, which elſe it cannot: So, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is the eye and glaſſe of the Soule, the Soule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds her ſelfe, and ſees her owne beauty or deformity, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the print or ſtampe of euery action which it hath committed, eyther good or euill, giuing euidence to God and to her ſelfe, and iudging eyther for vs or againſt vs, as the deed requires.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The ſeate of Conſcience.</label> Some haue placed this Conſcience in the <hi>Will</hi> or <hi>Heart</hi> of man, ſome in the <hi>Memory,</hi> ſome in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> which hath a two-fold operation, the firſt <hi>Theoricall,</hi> and thus the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding onely contemplates and conſidereth of truth and falſhood, but goeth no further. The ſecond <hi>Practicall,</hi> and ſo it conſidereth euery particular circumſtance, &amp; ſearcheth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good or euill, &amp; vnder the later of theſe Conſcience is comprehended: not that conſcience is a part of a part, only circumſcribed in the vnderſtanding as a part of that: for though the vnderſtanding bee the Throne and Palace of Conſcience, where it exerciſeth the principall offices, yet as the ſoule is <hi>Tota in toto,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Similitude. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>&amp; tota in qualibet parte corporis:</hi> whole in the whole, and whole in euery part of the body; (though chiefly in the <hi>head</hi> or <hi>heart</hi>) ſo the <hi>Conſcience</hi> is whole in the whole ſoule, keeping a Court in the whole; and yet exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (not euery part, for the ſoule is indiuiſible in reſpect of parts, but) euery faculty and power of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> it is a Iudge diſcerning the actions, and giuing ſentence to acquire or condemne, according to that <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> with which it is enlightened.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:7186:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the <hi>memory</hi> it is a <hi>Regiſter,</hi> to witneſſe what is done, or what is not done. In the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Affections,</hi> an executioner <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to puniſh or reward with ioy or griefe, with boldnes or terror, according to the fact or feeling of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The manner of working in the Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</label> The manner of working is by a kinde of practicall ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme; The <hi>Maior</hi> is that Law ſeated in the <hi>vnderſtanding:</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> brought by the memory; I remember I haue done or not done according to that Law of God: The <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> followeth by a ſecond act of the vnderſtanding; therefore I am guilty or not guilty, and ſhewed in the heart or will, by feare or ioy, or ſuch kind of affections.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt, the vnderſtanding knoweth or is enlightened with a rule or law, by which it tryeth (as gold is tryed with a touchſtone) the good or euill of euery action; and according to the nature and ſtrength of this knowledge the ſenſe or ſtroke of Conſcience is felt in the hart, either by ioy or griefe, by peace or trouble, by feare or boldneſſe, or the like. If the knowledge be naturall, ariſing only from that light of nature, or thoſe ſparkes of knowledge (both of God and of his Law) not quite extinct by <hi>Adams</hi> fall, but left in man, to make him voyd of all excuſe, then is the ſtroke or force of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence not ſo powerfull, making anſwer onely to that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with which it is enlightened: But if, beſides this light of nature, our vnderſtandings are informed with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and of his Will (as God in ſacred Scriptures hath reuealed himſelfe vnto his Church,) then is the force of Conſcience much more powerfull, affecting the ſoule with ioy or greife, with peace or trouble, according to the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vnderſtanding, and application to the will and heart of man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And next (this foundation being layd, this rule and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in a read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe) the <hi>Memory</hi> giueth euidence of all our Actions, and of the circumſtance and manner how they haue beene done, either openly or in ſecret, of which the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> taking knowledge, by a ſecond Act it layeth them to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that Rule and Law of God, with which it is enlightned: and iudgeth whether the Actions be agreeable or contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:7186:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label>4 A deſcription of Conſcience.</label> Vpon which there is preſently a reflection and application to the <hi>Will;</hi> by which the <hi>Heart,</hi> as by a Diuine power, is ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and moued with affections, according to the nature of that <hi>Knowledge, Act,</hi> and <hi>Application,</hi> by meane whereof, it is touched and affected. For knowledge muſt goe before the feeling or ſtroke of Conſcience, thy heart can neuer feele that to be good, or euill, which thy mind knoweth not to bee ſo: and according to the meaſure, nature, and quality of thy knowledge, ſuch will bee the teſtimony and feeling of thy Conſcience: a knowledge which is light, or doubting, or vncertaine, makes a light and eaſie ſtroke, affecting the <hi>Heart</hi> but little, either with ioy or griefe, with feare or boldneſſe, or the like; But on the contrary part, if the knowledge bee holy, ſound, and good, grounded on the word of truth right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtood, then will it make a heauy ſtroke vpon the Conſcience, if the deed be euill; as it doth a heauenly ioy and peace vnto the ſoule if that thy actions be good and anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Word and Law of God. And thus is Conſcience not onely <hi>Lux intellectus,</hi> the light of the vnderſtanding (as Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> intimates) but (if it be rightly informed &amp; follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>Norma vitae,</hi> the rule and guide of all our life, as St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> obſerues. And now by what hath beene ſpoken you haue ſeene a glympſe of Conſcience (though not a perfect ſight) and may remember it with this or the like deſcription. <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not barely an Act or habit of the ſoule, or will, or vnderſtanding, (for it produceth acts, and acts may ceaſe to be, as habits may bee loſt; but Conſcience can neuer ceaſe to be, nor can it be loſt, though it may loſe the vſe (for a time) as a man may loſe the vſe of <hi>Reaſon</hi> in the time of <hi>Drunkennes</hi>) It is therefore rather an office, or faculty, or power of the ſoule, created in man by God, and ſet within him both as a witneſſe and a Iudge, yea a comforter to the godly, and a tormenter too vnto the wicked. Conſcience is no Forraigner or ſtrange Inhabitant, but an In-dweller, remaining with vs, yea within us, which after ſinne, torments; and after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>forteth the ſoule of man. Conſcience is the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder,</hi> the principall ſecretary to regiſter all our thoughts, our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7186:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> words and actions. It is like a Chryſtall-glaſſe, wherein the ſoule beholds herſelfe, and ſeeth what ſhe hath done, &amp; what ſhe hath left vndone. It is <hi>Priuata Lex,</hi> a priuate Law to iudge within herſelfe, from which theres no appeale, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: For when the Ciuill Law, and Common Law haue done, then this begins. It is the <hi>Lord-Keeper,</hi> the <hi>Chancellor,</hi> the <hi>Vice-Deus,</hi> the <hi>Vnder-God,</hi> who keepeth a Chancery in the ſoule of man, and without all partiality, being rightly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of euery circumſtance, giueth iuſt and righteous iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The power of Conſcience.</label> Great is the power and ſtrength of Conſcience. It is vnder God indeed, and ſubiects a man to God; becauſe God can binde the Conſcience: but it is aboue all men that are in the world, for though Kings are bound in Chaines,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6.</note> and Nobles in linkes of Iron, yet Conſcience can no man binde; they may bind thy body and caſt that into priſon: but thy conſcience they cannot bind; it is aboue their ſtrength and beyond their power, they are not able to doe it; And yet Conſcience is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to bind all, not only inferiour perſons, but Kings, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Iudges of the earth. It is aboue all, and that in reſpect of a fourefold <hi>Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>The Offices of Conſcience.</label> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt Office is the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> for a mans conſcience is as a thouſand witneſſes to acquire or condemne before God or men, and the voyce of conſcience is far more ſure then the report of many others:<note place="margin">Seneca lib. de Mor.</note> for as <hi>Seneca</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, <hi>Falli ſapè poterit fama, conſcientia nunquam:</hi> the report of others may oftentimes deceiue thee, but (for thine owne actions) thy conſcience neuer, that will giue true euidence, with or againſt thee, for what thou haſt done, or left vndone.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Conſcience hath a ſecond office, and this is the <hi>Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>Tryall</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and in this ſhe exceeds all outward <hi>Tryals.</hi> For men in tryalls often erre becauſe the <hi>Truth</hi> is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from them, and cannot eaſily be found: but conſcience in tryall of our actions knoweth the truth: ſhee is an eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, one of which is better then a thouſand; and ſhee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from grounds and principles within, knowne to her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and therefore quick-ſighted conſcience ſoone perceiues
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7186:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> which way the ballance draweth, the thoughts meane while accuſing or excuſing for the fact, (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth it,) <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p>Tryall being made, ſhee proceedeth vnto her third office; And this is the <hi>Iudgement</hi> of Conſcience, in which ſhe is alſo excellent, for ſhe hath the keyes of binding and looſing, of abſoluing or condemning. If ſhee binde, tis faſter then with fetters of braſſe; if ſhee looſe, ſhee ſetteth as much at liberty, as the Angell did <hi>Peter</hi> from his Chaines:<note place="margin">Act. 12.7.</note> and if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne a matter of fact, her ſentence being paſt, vpon euidence giuen and tryall made, there is no recall, ſhe admits no writt of <hi>Error,</hi> oftentimes abuſed to make the ſute immortall and more coſtly then the cauſe is worth; but this is no deede of Conſcience:<note place="margin">Ambroſ. ſerm. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> And Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> giueth the reaſon, <hi>Sine excuſatione eſt, qui Conſcientiae ſuae iudicio condemnatur:</hi> Hee is without all excuſe, who is condemned of his owne Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; he who is iudged by another, may ſometimes hope for pardon, but hee who is iudged by himſelfe, of whom ſhould hee require it? of none but God who is aboue the Conſcience. And therefore by true faith and true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance he muſt fly from himſelfe to Chriſt, before he can haue peace.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And laſtly, Iudgement being pronounced <hi>Execution</hi> is not delayed, which is her laſt <hi>Office:</hi> and this ſhee performes in her owne perſon; for ſentence is no ſooner giuen, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſhe affects the innocent with peace and ioy vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and the guilty with feare and torture that cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. This iuſt reward is not deferred till aftertimes, but beginneth in preſent, both to the one and to the other. The godly haue their <hi>Heauen</hi> begunne on earth,<note place="margin">Philip. 4.7.</note> enioying that ſame <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> which paſſeth all vnderſtanding. And the wicked enter into <hi>Hell</hi> before they dye,<note place="margin">Marke 9.44. Eſay 66.24.</note> hauing that worme of Conſcience their companion, which ſhall liue for euer to torment them,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtom. Hom. <hi>16.</hi> ad popu. Antioch.</note> ſo Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> As he that liueth in wickedneſſe is puniſhed before he goe to <hi>Hell,</hi> (being ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Conſcience) ſo he that liueth in righteouſneſſe, before he goe to <hi>Heauen</hi> enioyeth a ioy vnſpeakeable.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:7186:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label>Preuention of obiection.</label> And thus you ſee what Conſcience is, and what her acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, by which ſhee is diſcerned from other faculties of the ſoule, and acts or actions of the minde and will of man;<note place="margin">Perkins.</note> as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, opinion, ſcience, faith, prudence,</hi> or the like. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> ſimply conceiues a thing to bee, or not to bee: <hi>Opinion</hi> iudgeth it to bee probable or contingent: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Science</hi> knoweth it to bee certaine or euident: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Faith</hi> is a perſwaſion whereby wee beleeue things that are not, or aſſent to the truth of things that are: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>Prudence</hi> diſcerneth what is fit to bee done, and what to bee left vndone. But <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> goeth further then all theſe, for it not onely giues euidence and examines, but determines or giues ſentence of things done, by ſaying vnto vs, this was done, this was not done; this may bee done, this may not bee done; this was well done, this was ill done: and in execution, either rewarding or puniſhing vs for what wee haue done, or left vndone, either good or euill. Thus is Conſcience of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature, being placed in the middeſt, as an Ambaſſador betweene God and man, and giuen by God vnto him for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall companion: It is like thy ſhadow, <hi>Nec fugere, nec fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ris,</hi> thou canſt neither flie from it, not make it flie from thee: Ague fits are ſhaken off, this neuer,<note place="margin">Ruth 1.16.</note> but like <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomie,</hi> it will follow thee whither ſoeuer thou goeſt: the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhall leaue the ſoule, and the ſoule ſhall leaue the body for a time, but the Conſcience ſhall neuer leaue the ſoule, but whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer the ſoule goeth, thither ſhall the Conſcience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire; and in what ſtate thy Conſcience is when thou depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt out of this life, in the ſelfe ſame it ſhall meete thee in that day of iudgment, and ſhall remaine with thee, either a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or a torment to thy ſoule for euer. It is true (that in this life) Conſcience ſometimes is not felt, but as it were benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or ſenſleſſe; and then vnto the godly man (who mourns becauſe he cannot feele that ioy of conſcience which his ſoule deſires) 'tis like our Sauiour faſt aſleepe in the bottome of the ſhippe, while his Diſciples were toſſed with the waues.<note place="margin">Mat. 8.24.</note> And to the wicked (who could wiſh it were dead) indeed, 'tis like the muzzled Maſtife tied in chaines, which can neither barke nor bite, and therfore lets the theefe commit his wickedneſſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7186:10"/> with pleaſure. But when this Conſcience is awakened, or the chaines thereof vntied, then to the godly 'tis like Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the ſoueraigne comfort of the ſoule. But to the wicked, like the Maſtiffe ſet at libertie; or like a Fiend of Hell to rend and teare his ſoule in peece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Conſcience in this world is often as a booke ſhut vp, or fountaine ſealed; but at the day of iudgment it ſhall bee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and then both good and bad ſhall feele the power of it. <hi>The Bookes were opened</hi> (ſaith the Text) And it is S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> obſeruation,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Pſal. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conſcientia eſt codex, in quo quotidiana pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta conſcribuntur,</hi> The Conſcience is a booke, in which our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinnes are written; and ſo is our righteouſneſſe alſo, our good actions as well as our euill; &amp; both theſe ſhall be brought to light when the bookes ſhall bee opened.<note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>20.</hi> de Ciuit. dei. cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> So S. <hi>Auguſtine, virtute diuina fiet, &amp;c.</hi> By the diuine power it ſhall be brought to paſſe, that to euery one, their workes either good or euill ſhall bee called in memory, and with a wonderfull celerity by the eie of the minde they ſhall bee ſeene, that the Conſcience may either excuſe or accuſe; and as that beareth witneſſe, ſo ſhall the owner of it be either ſaued or condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vſe.</label> Oh then beloued! How ſhould this opening of the Book of Conſcience at that laſt generall Aſſiſes, moue euery Chriſtian in the meane time, to labour earneſtly for the auoyding of a bad, and obtaining of a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>1 An euill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in reſpect of faith.</label> Conſcience is either <hi>de fide,</hi> or <hi>de moribus;</hi> it concerneth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>faith,</hi> or <hi>life,</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> or <hi>practice</hi> of a man: a good conſcience in both is to be ſought after, and a bad in both to be auoided. If wee looke vpon <hi>Conſcience</hi> in the firſt reſpect, wee ſhall finde ſome Conſciences to bee euill, led aſide to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and oftentimes to hereſie, by wrong information, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceiued by Satans ſubtilties, or drawne away by falſe teachers,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1, 2, 3. and 13, 14.</note> of whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> giueth warning, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. and S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſeconds him in his ſecond Epiſtle &amp; ſecond Chapter. And 'tis a wonder to ſee what miſery theſe deceiued ſoules doe willingly endure, rather then offend their conſciences in any thing (though blinded by a falſe intelligenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) witneſſe the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Gentiles, and ſuperſtitious Iewes (of whoſe mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7186:10"/> the Scripture giueth a teſtimony) and many Chriſtians alſo, whoſe weak and tender ſoules are much afflicted for want of growth in ſpirituall vnderſtanding, and ſound iudgment in knowledge of the truth; (and therefore both to be pittied and prayed for) ſo ſtrong are the bands of <hi>ignorance</hi> (worſe then Aegyptian darkneſſe) &amp; ſo powerful is Conſcience (once awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened) to keepe a man in obedience to that rule and law,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.22.</note> with which it is enlightened, and of the truth of which it is perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; yea, to the ſhadow of that truth, with which ſometimes (in ſtead of ſubſtance) it is deceiued.</p>
            <p>To preuent this <hi>erroneous Conſcience;</hi> to keepe our ſelues from it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t from vs, it is heauenly counſell which is giuen by good S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> that bleſſed Diuine. Beloued, beleeue not euery ſpirit, but try the ſpirits whether they are of God, becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1. (and now eſpecially they are too common in our land) Search the Scriptures therefore, for in them is certainly eternall life: <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39. and try theſe Teachers by the law and teſtimony, the will of God reuealed in his word: if they ſpeake not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.20. And that thou maieſt bee ſure to ſpeed the better in this ſearch for truth;<note place="margin">Malach. 2.7.</note> to ſatisfie thy Conſcience in a time of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, aduiſe with thoſe who are truly learned and religious, and pray for the aſſiſtance of Gods gracious Spirit, that it will pleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him to lighten thy eies that thou ſleepeſt not in death, and to direct them aright to inform thy conſcience: and pray for others alſo (and I will pray with thee) that this good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may lighten thoſe that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Luc. 1.79,</note> and in the ſhadow of death, and guide their feet into the way of peace. And being thus guided by him who cannot erre, thou ſhalt bee ſure of a good Conſcience, which is alſo to be found as it hath relation to faith. <label>2 A good Conſci. in relation to Faith.</label> And this is a Conſcience rightly informed by the good Spirit, in the law and word of truth, the bleſſed guide to life eternall; the blacke cloudes of <hi>Ignorance</hi> being baniſhed, &amp; the vnderſtanding enlightened with the glorious beams of <hi>ſauing knowledge,</hi> from whence there ſpringeth a heauenly ioy and ſolace to the ſoule: for though the Chriſtian knoweth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7186:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> here but in part,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> and ſeeth but darkly as in a glaſſe, his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge being but ignorance and darkeneſſe it ſelfe, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that bleſſed light, with the brightneſſe whereof our minds ſhall ſhine in heauen. Yet hath the life of <hi>Grace</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent difference from the ſtate of <hi>Nature;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.14. 2 Cor. 4.4.</note> the <hi>naturall man</hi> is blind, and cannot ſee the things of God, and therefore wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in feare or deſperate madneſſe, not knowing whither hee goeth, ſinning againſt his <hi>naturall,</hi> or following the checks of an <hi>erroneous Conſcience</hi> to his owne deſtruction.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.28. 1 Cor. 2 15.</note> But the <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man</hi> diſcerneth all (yea ſeeth the ſecret) things of God, being directed by that ſacred guide of truth, in the light of which he walketh on boldly, with ioy of heart and heauenly ſtedfaſtneſſe, through the darke and gloomy wilderneſſe of this world (which is full of clouds and miſts of errour) to that bleſſed Canaan of perpetuall happineſſe, where is the light and glory of that truth which can neuer be extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue briefly ſhewed the difference betweene the good and euill Conſcience, in reſpect of faith and knowledge; the one rightly informed and directed to the light of Saints; the other led aſide by error to eternall darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Of Conſcience, as it hath relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to life and practice.</label> But my intent is now to ſpeake eſpecially of Conſcience, as it concernes the good or euill life of man. And this is either good or euill, according to the good or euill actions which a man committeth. For Conſcience at firſt was good before the fall of our firſt Parents, but after that, they ſoone did feels, and that by wofull experience, the happineſſe of a good, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of an euill conſcience: therefore <hi>They hid themſelues from God and were afraid,</hi> becauſe their <hi>Conſcience</hi> tould them they were naked. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.10, 11. And this euill of Conſcience they left to their poſterity, as heires of their corruption. And as <hi>Conſcience</hi> is euill by corrupted nature,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> naturally accuſing man of inbred wickedneſſe: ſo groweth it worſe and worſe by actuall tranſgreſſion. And hence it commeth to paſſe, that as there are diuers kinds of ſinnes committed in the world; ſo are there diuers kinds of euill conſciences amongſt the ſonnes of men, but all of them to be deteſted, and their ſociety eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from vs.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7186:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſcience euill. </seg>1</label> The firſt is <hi>Conſcientia mortua,</hi> a dead and cauterized Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; <hi>A Conſcience ſeared with a hot iron,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. Theſe Conſciences are full of ſin, yet feele it not, they are aſleepe and cannot ſee it; <hi>Their minds are blind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 12.25. Exod. 9.35. 1. Sam. 8.6. Luc. 18.2. Ierem. 3.3.</note> like <hi>Iobs</hi> wanderers: their will peruerſe, like <hi>Pharaohs:</hi> they are left of God, as <hi>Saul:</hi> they are careleſſe, like the vniuſt <hi>Iudge, Not fearing God, nor reuerencing man: They haue harlots fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads,</hi> as the Lord complaines againſt the Iewes; and their ſtate is miſerable, becauſe 'tis hard and difficult to returne; for, <hi>Can the Blacke-moore change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots? then may yee doe good which are accuſtomed to doe euill. Ieremiah</hi> 13.23.</p>
            <p>This Conſcience is as bad as may be, and yet it is common amongſt prophane ones in the world, which makes them ſin with greedineſs, running poſt-haſt to drunkenneſſe, to whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and prophaneſſe; breaking of Gods Sabbaths without Conſcience; for why? This Booke of Conſcience now is clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but they ſhall one day feele the terror of it, when as the Booke of Conſcience ſhall bee opened.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſcience. </seg>2</label> There is a ſecond <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and thats as contrary vnto this, as is the Pole <hi>Ant-articke</hi> to the <hi>Articke,</hi> the South vnto the North; and this is <hi>Conſcientia desperata,</hi> a deſperate Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, too ſenſible both of the ſting of ſinne, and wrath of God againſt it; this was in <hi>Saul, Achitophel,</hi> and <hi>Iudas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 31.4. 2. Sam. 17.23. Mat. 27.5.</note> it is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of Conſcience vpon the wicked in this life (for here in part to ſome the booke is opened, therefore their Hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth;) but at the day of Iudgment they ſhall feele the ſting and worme of Conſcience in more fearefull manner, becauſe the booke of Conſcience then ſhall bee at large vnfolded.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſcience. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, another Conſcience followeth, and this is as it were a middle betweene both the former; not ſo dead as that it can be ſenſible of no iniquity; nor ſo quicke as that it ſhould be touched with euery ſinne: it is rightly named, <hi>Conſcientia ſpatioſa,</hi> a large and ſpatious <hi>Conſcience,</hi> for it can hold a volume of impiety; eſpecially a <hi>Delilah</hi> or <hi>Agag</hi> ſhall bee welcome;<note place="margin">Iudges 16.4. 1. Sam. 15.9.</note> a beloued vice, or princely ſin it makes no Conſcience of. This is like <hi>Cheuerill</hi> or <hi>Kids</hi> leather, becauſe 'twill ſtretch, and is ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7186:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> farre from ſtraining at a <hi>Gnat,</hi> that it with eaſe will ſwallow downe a <hi>Cammell.</hi> And this Conſcience is no Farraigner but a free <hi>Denizon,</hi> it dwelleth amongſt vs, (more is the pitty) you ſhall meet it as you trauell in many countryes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Sometimes amongſt the <hi>Clergie,</hi> it is entertained of ſuch, who make no conſcience with what <hi>corruption</hi> they obtain the <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>ſoules</hi> ſo they may get it; and then they care as little for to feed them; except it bee with meat that is worſe then poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, their own bad example, by which they bring themſelues and others to deſtruction.<note place="margin">Luc. 11.35. Mat. 5.13, 14.</note> A wofull thing when that the light is darkned, and the ſalt hath loſt his ſauour; when as the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers life ſhould lead to heauen, it leads men to perdition.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Sometimes amongſt the <hi>Lawyers</hi> it is entertained of ſuch, who make no conſcience to excite and ſtirre vp men to need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſuites;<note place="margin">Luc. 11.46.</note> encouraging to warre when peace is better, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Cauſes with their armes wide open, and receiuing fees with both hands; with one, to ſpeake; with the other, to hold their peace: And when they haue got a man to bee their priſoner, they feed him then with bread and water of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vntill his purſe bee emptie, or his ſtate conſumed, what time they ſend him home amongſt his neighbours to end the controuerſie with two honeſt men in ſtead of twelue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Sometimes this large and ſpacious Conſcience is amongſt the <hi>Gentry,</hi> where it is entertained of ſuch who make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of moſt vile oppreſſions, grinding the faces of the poore, &amp; racking their Tenants at ſo high a rate, that though themſelues, their wiues &amp; children are their Land-lords ſlaues, yet can they not be kept from beggery. And as little Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doe they make of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> (a ſin as common and worſe then the former) whiles they are not content to robbe the Church of all her ancient rights, but in prophane and wicked manner, by ſymoniacall compacts, ſell both themſelues, their <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>people</hi> to the Deuill; and this they thinke is no ſin, it is ſo ordinary (becauſe their Conſcience is now aſleepe) but they ſhall one day finde it ſo, when as the booke of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall bee opened.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Sometimes amongſt the <hi>Iurors,</hi> and that at time of <hi>Aſſiſe</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:7186:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> and <hi>Seſſions,</hi> you may eaſily finde this Conſcience to bee in thoſe who make no conſcience of an oath, but contrary to their <hi>oath</hi> will giue their <hi>verdict,</hi> not as <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> would direct them, but as malice or affection leads them. But woe to ſuch, for their conſcience one day ſhall bee both a <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and a <hi>Iudge</hi> againſt them, when once the Booke of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall bee opened.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And commonly this Conſcience is amidſt the <hi>Common</hi> ſort, eſpecially inferior <hi>Officers,</hi> who ſhould be euen the life of Law, in bringing wickedneſſe before the Iudge, and after ſentence giuen, in ſeeing Iuſtice executed. But they haue <hi>Conſciences</hi> as wide as hell; either for feare of greatneſſe, or for loue of baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſmothering vile enormities, which not being kild in time, haue filled the land with ſinnes that cry for vengeance: And this, though men be ſworne, yet doe they ſuffer, becauſe their booke of Conſcience is not opened. And thus you ſee the large and ſpacious Conſcience, and the ſeuerall ſorts of men by whom it is entertained.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſcience. </seg>4</label> There is yet, <hi>Conſcientia ſuperſtitioſa,</hi> a ſuperſtitious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, moſt commonly amongſt our ignorant Papiſts, blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſhadowes, circumſtances, ceremonies; deceiued with <hi>ſhewes,</hi> and ſelfe-conceited opinions of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſality, infallibility of iudgment, ſucceſſion of gouernment, and the like; being wedded to <hi>will-worſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay. Coloſſ. 2.18.</note> and ſporting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the priſon of ignorance, vntill it pleaſeth God to bring them (as he doth many of them before they die) out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o light, and from the power of condemning error, vnto the ſauing Truth of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſcience. </seg>5</label> And there is <hi>Conſcientia ſcrupuloſa,</hi> a ſcrupulous or dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſcience, <label>1 A dubious Conſcience in matters of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</label> which if it be in <hi>Subſtance</hi> in the tender-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtian, aſſaulted with the violence of Satans ſleights, or ouer-burdened with the ſight and ſenſe of ſelfe-corruption, or terrified with too much contemplation of Gods fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgments due to ſinne (for the guilt of which the Conſcience is accuſed) and affected with too little of <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Chriſts precious merits, and thoſe gratious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of pardon and freedom from Gods direfull vengeance, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7186:13"/>
               <label>The cauſes of doubting in a tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</label> true repentance, and faith in Chriſt. If this bee the cauſe of feare and ſcruple in this kinde of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brings the weake and feeble Chriſtian to the mouth of Hell, and pits-brinke of deſpaire: Then though in the end it turneth vnto the good of Gods Elect, to moue them to a tryall of their ſtates; to <hi>ſearch</hi> and <hi>proue</hi> their <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>conſciences,</hi> to finde out what's amiſſe, and what's the cauſe of this their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> doubting; whether their ſinnes, which perhaps haue long lien hidden, kept ſecret in the cloſet of their hearts, not truly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſeene nor felt, nor yet repented of; or their <hi>ſecurity,</hi> in which before they were lulled aſleepe, being idle and neglecting to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> vnfold their Booke of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> Or their <hi>want</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> in Chriſt, and firme <hi>affiance</hi> on Gods true and neuer-failing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Or their <hi>truſt</hi> too much vnto <hi>themſelues,</hi> ſeeking for <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> more in the meaſure of their owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then in the free imputed righteouſneſſe of Chriſt: Or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> laſtly, in their <hi>ignorance,</hi> and erroneous iudgment of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſtate, here in the Church thats militant, and thoſe many combats we muſt vndergoe, before we paſſe from all our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or get within the gates of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> (for any one of theſe may bring a Chriſtian from the rock of ſtedfaſtnes, to a world of doubts and feares:) Though in the end (I ſay) theſe feares and ſcruples may procure this good vnto the ſoul, to ſee it ſelfe and find the cauſe of this diſtreſſe; yet is this ſickneſſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and the cure is difficult: And therfore here the weak and <hi>tender conſcience</hi> had neede to <hi>pray,</hi> and ſeeke a wiſe, a holy, and a good Phyſitian, who like Chriſt, may poure in <hi>wine</hi> and <hi>oyle,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpell</hi> tempered together with piety and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">Luc. 10.34.</note> and applyed with a ſoft and gentle hand, vntill the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience being rightly informed, may ſee the cauſe, and labour to remoue it, that ſo a ſetled ſtedfaſtneſſe may bee obtained.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A dubious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</label> And how this may bee, I ſhall ſhew the meanes (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> when I come to ſpeak of <hi>Conſcience</hi> as 'tis good: to which I rather refer this Conſcience (though it be ſicke, &amp; weak, and doubtful) becauſe it may be in the beſt &amp; deareſt ſaints of God.</p>
            <p>But if this Doubting bee in <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> as tis often in the ſelfe-conceited Separatiſts, who are ouer nice and curious, in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7186:13"/> tything Minte, Annis and Cummin: in ſtanding vpon ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, ceremonies, and things indifferent. But too careleſſe otherwiſe, letting the greater matters of the Law alone, (as our Sauiour ſometimes told the Phariſes (in this reſpect) their predeceſſors.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.23.</note>) Then though their deſire bee good to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contrary or againſt their conſcience: yet were it farre better, to ſeeke and labour that their Conſcience may bee rightly inſtructed; that being obedient vnto gouernment, they offend not thoſe are weake; nor make a rent and Schiſme, in the ſeameleſſe Coat (or Church) of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Iohn 19.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Many more there are of euill conſciences, but I leaue them all, and deſire we may all leaue theſe, becauſe they all are euill, and at laſt, if not preuented, will bring their entertainers vnto ruine, when once the booke of Conſcience ſhall bee opened. For as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Bern. lib. de Conſcient.</note> there is no puniſhment greater then an euill Conſcience: and he giueth the reaſon, becauſe of all our ſinnes, Conſcience is the witneſſe, the Iudge, the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the priſon; it is Conſcience which puniſheth, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which condemneth.</p>
            <p>The like hath Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> Saint <hi>Hierom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil. Orat. <hi>23.</hi> de Iudicio. Greg. lib. <hi>13.</hi> moral. cap. <hi>13.</hi> Hierom. in Iſay lib. <hi>16.</hi> Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>52.</hi> in Gen.</note> and diuers other of the Fathers. Great is the terror of an euill Conſcience; it was Conſcience (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) that moued <hi>Abimelech</hi> to ſend away <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 26. It was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that affrighted <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren in Aegypt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.21. It was Conſcience that changed the countenance of King <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> while his thoughts did trouble him ſo that the ioynts of his loynes were looſed, and his knees ſmote one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another. <hi>Daniel,</hi> 5.6. It was Conſcience that made <hi>Foelix</hi> tremble while <hi>Paul</hi> did reaſon of righteouſneſſe, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Iudgement to come. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. Though by the grace of God in <hi>Faith</hi> and true <hi>Repentance,</hi> a man may flye from the euill of conſcience, yet conſcience and the ſentence of her Court cannot be eſcaped.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>3.</hi> de verbis Iſaiae. <hi>Vidi Dom.</hi>
               </note> And S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> giueth the reaſon. <hi>Hoc enim tribunal non pecunia corrumpitur, non adulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus acquieſcit, &amp;c.</hi> This tribunall of Conſcience is not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with money, nor will it ceaſe from ſentence with fayre ſpeeches; it is Diuine, and will performe that for which God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7186:14"/> hath made it. And this eſpecially ſhall be ſeene when that the Booke of Conſcience ſhall be opened. Let this ſuffice to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade euery Chriſtian by flying euill to auoyd an euill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. A word or two which may moue vs to ſeeke for a good <hi>conſcience,</hi> that ioy may be vnto vs when the books are opened.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The excellency of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</label> A good <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a continuall feaſt (as the wiſe man ſpeakes) <hi>Prou.</hi> 15.15. It is rich and beautifull like the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Solomon;</hi> It is a <hi>field</hi> of <hi>bleſſedneſſe,</hi> a <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of pleaſure, the <hi>ioy</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> the <hi>treaſure</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Arke</hi> of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant,</hi> the <hi>Palace</hi> of God, and the <hi>Habitation</hi> of the bleſſed <hi>Spirit,</hi> as <hi>Hugo de Anima</hi> deſcribes it, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. It is as the <hi>Apple</hi> of the <hi>Eie,</hi> the <hi>tree</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> and the <hi>Bed</hi> of the <hi>Soule,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Chriſtian deſireth to reſt, that hee may paſſe from that ſweet and quiet reſt of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in this world, to that reſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall in the world to come.<note place="margin">Paeſ. in Iacob.</note> It is related of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> that when a Roman died, who while he liued was infinitely in debt, (yet liued in pleaſure) that of all his houſholdſtuffe which at his death was to bee ſold, <hi>Caeſar</hi> did onely wiſh to buy his <hi>Bed,</hi> for that (ſaith hee) muſt needes bee of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertue, which could make the owner ſleepe, who ought ſo much. And if that <hi>Bed</hi> was iudged worth ſo much; then certainely this <hi>Bed</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which can giue ſuch quiet reſt, amongſt a world of troubles, muſt needes bee prized at a higher rate, and therefore more to bee deſired. For what greater happineſſe can there bee vnto a Chriſtian in this life, then to enioy a good, a peaceable, and a quiet <hi>Conſcience,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if euer he haue felt a wounded Conſcience, or beene af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted once with doubts, and feares, and terrors (like a man thats toſſed in a raging and tempeſtuous Sea;) then is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comparable vnto this peace of Conſcience, nor any knoweth how good, how excellent it is, but they that haue it. And yet a <hi>quiet Conſcience</hi> is not alwayes good, nor peace ſo profitable vnto the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <label>1 Some peace of Conſcience not good.</label> For firſt, the Conſcience that is <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>ignorant,</hi> may bee at peace and quiet, becauſe it neither ſeeth the filth of ſin, nor knoweth the Law of God; nor vnderſtandeth what vertue is commanded, or what vice forbidden: or if it doe, tis but as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7186:14"/> men ſee ſtarres in a darke and cloudy night, onely the great ones; not conſidering the ſtrictneſſe of obedience which God requires vnto his Law: therefore it feeleth not ſinne, nor is it troubled for iniquity, becauſe it knoweth it not, but walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on boldly to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And ſuch a peace is that which may be in a <hi>Conſcience</hi> thats <hi>ſecure</hi> and <hi>careleſſe,</hi> ſo ouer-buſied with the entizing pleaſures or profits of this world; or lulled aſleepe in that bewitching cradle of ſinnes darke impurity, that ſuch a man can finde no leaſure, no not to dreame of <hi>Heauen;</hi> or if he doe, hee ſoone forgets his dreame, and falleth toward <hi>Hell</hi> before hee bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And laſtly, ſuch a peace is that, thats in a <hi>Conſcience</hi> dead, or feared, made ſenſleſſe with the cuſtome of iniquity; tis with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life, and therefore feeleth no warre, (whiles the Deuill that ſtrong man armed, keepeth the Palace,) but is at peace,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.21.</note> vntill the Trumpet ſound vnto the <hi>Battell,</hi> and Gods mighty power awaken it from this benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med Lethargie, vnto the fearfull ſight of ſinne, and then tis like a roaring <hi>Lyon</hi> to deuoure its owner. This is a peace thats full of bitterneſſe in the end: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bee taken heed of, as a thing moſt dangerous to the Soule.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> But whats the difference may ſome man ſay, betweene this euill peace of an euill conſcience, and that which is to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; that happy comfort of a good and quiet Conſcience?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> I anſwer. The good and quiet <hi>Conſcience</hi> rightly informed, agreeth in this with that which is blind, or dead, or careleſſe, that both are quiet and peaceable; but there is a difference in their peace and quietneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The difference betweene true and falſe peace of Conſcience.</label> For firſt, the <hi>Conſcience</hi> that is dead, or blind, or careleſſe, is quiet and at peace, becauſe it ſeeth not ſinne, nor doth it feele it; or if it doth, yet it is ſo lulled aſleepe with dead <hi>ſecurity,</hi> that it conſidereth not what good or hurt it brings vnto the ſoule: and therefore (for that time) it is inſenſible of any trouble, and a kind of peace or truce is taken, in which it liueth ſecure. But a good Conſcience is quiet and at peace, becauſe it feeleth ſin to be forgiuen, and vpon faith and true repentance beholdeth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7186:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> God the Father pacified, and well pleaſed in his <hi>Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, a dead, or blinde, or careleſſe Conſcience, is at peace, becauſe it feares not ſinne, (though oftentimes it is not free from terror of God iudgement) nor maketh it Conſcience of impiety, but is prophane and careleſſe, running on to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe without reſtraint. But a good Conſcience is ſo at peace, that yet it is fearefull of the leaſt impiety, leſt by admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the pleaſure of ſinne, it ſhould procure the diſpleaſure of God, who is ſo good and louing a Father in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, a blinde, or dead, or careleſſe Conſcience, though it be quiet, yet it comforteth not, nor can it get any true or found ioy vnto the ſoule.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> But a Conſcience pacified with the hope of pardon and aſſurance of Gods fauour, begets a ioy of ſoule which is vnutterable, cheriſhing the heart with diuine and heauenly mirth, euen in the middeſt of many dangers. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hee obſerueth an euill conſcience is a <hi>Bed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. de interpellat. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> that when a man ſhould ſleepe, it giueth him torments, feares and terrors in ſtead of quietneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bern. in Vigil. Natiuit. ſerm. <hi>3.</hi> Foelix conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia in qua lucta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men timoris &amp; laetitiae reperitur. &amp;c. Etſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imet à Iudice, ſperat à Saluatore, &amp;c. Quia non timor ſempiternus, ſed laetitia ſempi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna. <hi>1. Sam. 24 4, 5.</hi>
               </note>A Conſcience that is good, procures the contrary: not that a Conſcience good is alwayes free from ſenſe of trouble; for (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) happy is that Conſcience in which is found the combate of feare, and ioy; feare when it looketh on God as a iuſt Iudge puniſhing for ſinne, and ioy when it beholded him as a louing Father pardoning ſinne to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in Chriſt, and for the merits of his death and Paſſion. And the tender conſcience which is deare in ſight of God, is like a Spider that ſitteth within the Center of her web, and if a fly but touch the out-moſt thread, ſhee feeleth it inſtantly. Iuſt ſo the child of God is touched in Conſcience for the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſinne, like <hi>Dauid</hi> but for cutting off the lappe of <hi>Sauls</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is a <hi>Filiall Feare,</hi> which is and ought to bee in all the Sonnes of God, and tis the meanes for to preſerue a good and quiet <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Quest.</label> But how may this good conſcience be obtained? what muſt we doe to get it? that ſo we may take care to keepe it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> I anſwer. A good and quiet conſcience is a ſpeciall gift of God, to him therefore we muſt pray from whom comes euery
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7186:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> good and perfect gift:<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> and vſe the meanes which is the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to procure it.</p>
            <p>But before I ſhew what this meanes is,<note place="margin">Chriſt Ieſus the foundation of true peace of Conſcience. 2. Theſ. 3.16.</note> obſerue this by the way. There is now but one foundation vpon which this peace is builded: and without which there can bee no true peace vnto the ſoule. <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, had a good and peaceable conſcience, becauſe hee was free from ſinne, remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in his perfection.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> But now onely Chriſt Ieſus and the merits of his death and reſurrection, is the meanes of peace: God the Father being well pleaſed with vs in him;<note place="margin">Mat. 17.6.</note> and Chriſt purchaſing and procuring our peace by the blood of his Croſſe: <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.20. And this if wee apply rightly vnto our ſelues by a true and liuely faith, we are iuſtified, and being iuſtified by faith, we haue peace with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p>There is nothing that can make a good and peaceable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but the vertue of his blood:<note place="margin">Gen. 8.9.</note> the ſoule like <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue can find no reſt but in this Arke. Though our conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs not, yet is God greater then our conſcience,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.20.</note> and can eaſily find a cauſe of warre againſt vs, if he looke not vpon vs in his Sonne. It is this <hi>blood</hi> of ſprinkling that ſpeaketh better things then did the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Abel, Heb.</hi> 12.24. It is this <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt, who thorow the eternall ſpirit offered himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot to God, that can purge our conſciences from dead workes to ſerue the liuing God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. It is this onely that begets a good and quiet conſcience,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1. Rom. 6.4.6. Philip. 2.12. 2. Pet. 1.10.</note> taking away ſinnes <hi>guilt</hi> from vs: and crucifying ſinnes power in vs, that we may walke in newneſſe of life; working out our ſaluation with feare and trembling: and labouring to make our calling and election ſure. If thy conſcience ſting thee,<note place="margin">Numb. 21.9.</note> Chriſt is the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent that can cure thee. If the Law of thy conſcience, like Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> affright thee with terrors,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.23.</note> (worſe then <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> darkeneſſe,) in Chriſt is the Goſpell of light that can enlighten thine vnderſtanding, and lighten thy heart with ioy and gladneſſe. If the red Sea of thy troubled conſcience hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy paſſage to eſcape thy enemies that follow thee, and to come to the happineſs before thee; Chriſt is the way, the truth,<note place="margin">Iohn 14.6.</note> and the life, by whom thou maiſt paſſe boldly through the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7186:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> middeſt of dangers, to the Canaan of peace and freedome. This is the good Phyſitian who can cure all diſeaſes, and therefore eaſily procure peace vnto a troubled Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The meanes to get and keepe this peace of Conſcience.</label> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.19."</note> Firſt therefore to get and keepe this bleſſed peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, it is not to keepe merry company, to driue away me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, (as ſome imagine) but to keepe thy moſt <hi>holy faith,</hi> and preſerue the memory and application of this <hi>bloud</hi> of Ieſus, as a rich treaſure in thy ſoule: It is an Antidote to expell all the poyſon of Satans temptations, or thy owne corruptions; there is no ſinne thou haſt committed can be more powerfull to plead againſt thee,<note place="margin">Orizen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ulla ſpecies peceati tanta eſt qua non ſit ſuperior Ieſus. <hi>1 Iohn 1.7.</hi>
               </note> then (vpon faith and repentance) the merits of this bloud is to plead for thee, before the throne of Gods Iuſtice; nor any thing more effectuall to clenſe thee from all thy ſinnes; and therefore being rightly applied to free thee from conſcience of iniquity, and ſettle in thee a moſt ſweet and bleſſed peace.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A direction to peace.</label> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. ſuper Cant. Serm.</hi> 46. 1. <hi>Emundes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam ab omni inquina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Circundare tibi flores, &amp;c.</hi> 1. Meanes to procure peace. 2 Cor. 13.5. 1. Hinderance of peace.</note>And to direct thee further, follow Saint <hi>Bernards</hi> counſell: firſt clenſe thy Conſcience from all kind of pollution, from whatſoeuer hath or may offend thy conſcience, or procure the trouble of it; and next, gather thoſe ſweet flowers of ſpirituall graces of faith and good workes, of all heauenly vertues to decke thy ſoule that it may be a pleaſant temple for the good Spirit to dwell it. This is the way for to enioy a good and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Remedy.  </seg>1</label> And for the firſt of theſe, to put it in practice, trie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine thy ſelfe, ſearch into the ſecret of thy heart, and if thou find that thy ſinnes vnſeene or vnfelt haue procured thy woe, then is repentance the meanes to take away the doubt and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of thy Conſcience: for as a thorne within the fleſh will ſoone feſter and procure an ach and griefe,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.15.16.</note> from which thou canſt not be free, vntill the thorne be taken forth, and the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption drawne away: euen ſo whiles that any ſinne, though neuer ſo ſmall, lyeth cankering in thy heart, it will wound thy Conſcience with feares and doubts; and if it bee not remoued in time, procure a ſenſleſneſſe, (like a Gangrene) to kill both ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Hinderance. </seg>2</label> But if ſecurity be the cauſe, then muſt thou riſe from ſleepe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7186:16"/> and firſt make ſearch into thy Conſcience, leſt any ſecret thiefe <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Remedy.  </seg>1</label> haue ſtolne away thy heart (like <hi>Delilah</hi>) to rob thee of thy ſtrength,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.16.17</note> and by treaſon at vnawares to deliuer thee ouer to thy enemies: and next, be ſure to keepe a carefull watch ouer all <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Remedy.  </seg>2</label> thy thoughts, thy words, and workes, doe nothing contrary to the rule and law of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Hinderance. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, if it bee want of Faith, or feare, becauſe thou art not alwayes free from doubting <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Remedy.  </seg>1</label> : Firſt, vſe the meanes for to encreaſe thy faith, the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> the meditation of Gods gracious <hi>promiſes,</hi> and <hi>prayer</hi> vnto that good Spirit, who makes all theſe effectuall to the ſoule: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Remedy.  </seg>2</label> And next, know thisthat though thou art not alwayes free from doubting, thy faith may yet be true and good; for euen the beſt of Gods owne deareſt ones haue ſometimes felt a doubting in their ſoules, as <hi>Dauid, Ezekia, Iob,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> that bleſſed Saint,<note place="margin">Pſal. 88.14.15. Iſay 38.13.14. Iob 10.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>We are troubled on euery ſide,</hi> (ſaith he) yet not diſtreſſed; wee are perplexed, (or full of doubts) but yet deſpaire not, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Hinderance of peace. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, if thou haſt truſted too much vnto thy ſelfe, and ſought for peace where none was to be found; flye from thy ſelfe to Chriſt, who calleth in mercy all that bee afflicted, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Remedy.  </seg>1</label> promiſeth to giue them eaſe and reſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Hinderance. </seg>5</label> Laſtly, if ignorance of God, or of his law, or of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſtate, haue beene any meanes to hinder thee of thy peace; labor for knowledge (eſpecially in the Catechiſme or grounds <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Remedy.  </seg>1</label> of Chriſtian faith) and vſe the meanes with loue, delight, and any paines or coſt to get this ſpirituall vnderſtanding. For what greater miſerie then to walke in darkneſſe? or what more fearfull iudgement then to liue and die in ignorance? or what will ſooner bring a man to foule deſpaire, then to be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a Labyrinth of woe and trouble, and not to know the meanes how to be freed?</p>
            <p>Flye euill then, the euill of <hi>ſinne,</hi> the leaſt ſin in thought, in word, or deed, (as Hell it ſelfe) eſpecially knowne and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſinnes, thoſe ſinnes which are againſt the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, reſiſt and pray againſt, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did;<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note> and kill the ſeeds of ſinne, flye the occaſions, quench the fire betime, leſt it grow too big for thee;<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.9.</note> daſh Babylons children againſt the ſtones
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7186:17"/> while they be young. Thus ſhalt thou more eaſily conquer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity and get or keepe a quiet conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>2 Meanes to get peace of Conſcience.</label> But this is not all thats neceſſary to procure thy peace of Conſcience. Thou muſt not onely eſchew euill, but do good, to get and to preſerue this good and quiet conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>1 Doe good.</label> In the law of God <hi>Vice</hi> is not onely forbidden, but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> commanded, and obedience in both reſpects required, and that <hi>Vniuerſall Obedience:</hi> thou muſt with <hi>Dauid</hi> haue an eye <hi>to all</hi> Gods Commandements:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> thou muſt hide them in thy heart, that thou mayeſt not ſinne againſt God, thou muſt not take care of the <hi>firſt Table</hi> onely,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> and neglect the <hi>Second:</hi> nor of the <hi>Second</hi> only, and neglect the <hi>Firſt.</hi> God and thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour are both obiects of thy loue and obedience:<note place="margin">Luc. 10.27.</note> (though in a different reſpect) and towards both thou mayeſt not forget thy duty, (if thou deſireſt to keepe a good and a quiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.) One ſinne, yea the leſt ſin againſt any precept, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to condemne thee; for he that failes but in one poynt is guilty of all, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.10. and as if thou haſt heard but of one thiefe, hidden ſecretly in thy bed-chamber, it is ſufficient to keepe thee from ſleepe: ſo one ſinne of omiſſion or commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is able to hinder thee of this peace.</p>
            <p>
               <label>2 Doe good ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely.</label> Secondly, thy obedience muſt bee ſincere and vpright, thou muſt doe euery duty vprightly (though thou canſt not doe it perfectly) God requireth the heart: <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.7. Prou. 23.26. Deut. 6.5.</note> and the affections of thy heart and whole heart muſt be giuen vnto him. Gods pure eyes cannot endure to behold any impiety, neither ſhall any euill dwell with him; and much leſſe can hee endure hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, that our workes ſhould bee done in ſhew onely, and not in ſubſtance and ſincerity before him. It is onely the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and vpright man that can enioy a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>3 Doe good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly.</label> Thirdly, as God expects ſincerity, ſo he lookes for conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and perſeuerance in well doing, <note place="margin">Reuel. 2.10.</note> hee that will receiue the Crowne of life, he muſt be faithfull vnto the Death. It is not ſufficient to ſerue God in youth, and neglect him in age; nor to worſhip God on the Sabbath, and Satan all the weeke after; not to be holy amongſt thoſe which are holy, and prophane when thou commeſt into wicked company: This Wether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7186:17"/> Religion cannot ſtand with the peace of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they are like fire and water, light and darkeneſſe, one muſt of neceſſity expell the other.<note place="margin">Prou. 4.23.</note> Be not idle therefore or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, but watch diligently ouer thy ſelfe, and Conſcience, and exerciſe thy ſelfe (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did) that thou maiſt haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a Conſcience voyd of offence towards God,<note place="margin">Acts 24.26.</note> and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man. Thus mayeſt thou get this bleſſed peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, this aſſurance or Reconciliation betweene God and thee: and being once obtained, it can neuer finally bee loſt:<note place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> though the ſenſe of it may bee loſt for a time; the grace of faith and holineſſe, and aſſurance, or the feeling of grace being hid in thee, as the Sun vnder the clouds, <label>Similitude.</label> the fire couered with aſhes, the trees in the winter, a man in a trance, or the like,<note place="margin">The true way of a Chriſtian to the new Jeruſalem. <hi>The meanes of recouering the ſenſe of true peace.</hi>
               </note> (as at large I haue ſhewed, in another <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> to which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre thee.) And being loſt for a time, thou mayeſt againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer it; and the ſooner, and with more ioy, if thou vſe the good meanes, thoſe holy duties which are helpfull to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian for this ſpirituall exerciſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As firſt, priuate, frequent, and feruent prayer to God for his grace and fauour (as <hi>Dauid</hi> did;) <hi>Caſt mee not away from thy preſence, and take not thy holy Spirit from mee, restore vnto me the ioy of thy ſaluation, and ſtabliſh mee with thy free Spirit: Pſal.</hi> 51.11.12.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the remembrance of Gods ancient mercies, of his old louing kindneſſe towards thee, keeping thee from many dangers, deliuering thee from former troubles, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee many fauours, which he hath denied to others: this may perſwade thee, that though hee hide his face from thee for a time, yet hee will not finally forſake thee; for whom hee loueth once, he loueth him for euer in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the diligent attendance to the bleſſed <hi>meanes,</hi> to the Word and Sacraments, vſing them religiouſly, with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, faſting, meditation, and practice in thy life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, the priuate conference with the learned and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Paſtour of thy ſoule, and other good Chriſtians, whoſe prayer, counſell, and experience may bee a comfort vnto thee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7186:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> in thy ſpirituall deſertion, when thou wanteſt the feeling of this bleſſed peace, and ioy of <hi>conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, the often <hi>confeſſion</hi> of thy ſinnes before God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of thy <hi>repentance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.18.9, Prou. 28.13.</note> more ſeriouſly asking pardon and forgiueneſſe; and in all humility deſiring reconciliation in Chriſt. Thus haue the <hi>Saints</hi> of God; and thus (with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God) maieſt thou recouer this <hi>peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A requeſt to the conſcionable Reader.</label> And here, for this laſt point, let me beg one requeſt at thy hands; it is but a little one, ſay me not nay: I deſire it for the loue of God, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5.</note> and good of thine owne conſcience: Once a weeke at leaſt (if not once a day) ſhake off that dead <hi>ſecurity,</hi> in which the world lyeth buried, and ſpend one <hi>hower</hi> in <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination</hi> of thy ſelfe, in opening the <hi>booke</hi> of thy <hi>conſcience,</hi> in confeſſing thy ſelfe to God, and humbling thy ſoule before him:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.4.</note> goe into thy cloſet, and ſhut the doore after thee, and weepe in ſecret for thy owne ſinnes, and for the ſins of others, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that God may bee mercifull vnto thee. And if thy hard heart will not bee humbled, looke backe into thy life paſt, and call to remembrance thy old impieties, yea, forget not the ſinnes of thy youth (which <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth God not to remember) but ſpread them all before the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.6.</note> and aggrauate them by the ſeuerall circumſtances, that thou maiſt ſee how farre thou haſt erred from the law of God, which is a glaſſe to ſhew thee thy ſinnes: yea, iudge thy ſelfe for them, that thou maieſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not bee condemned of the Lord. And when thy Conſcience hath found thee guilty, then remember the direfull vengeance and fearefull iudgements of God due to ſinne; thinke how many <hi>hells</hi> thou haſt deſerued, if God ſhould enter into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> with thee. And if this will not humble thee, meditate further vpon that vnſpeakeable loue of God to thee in Chriſt, how when thou waſt a moſt vile and wicked miſcreant, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the gore blood of thy ſinfull corruption,<note place="margin">Ezeck. 16.4, 5, 6</note> defiled with the pollution of naturall and actuall tranſgreſſions, when none eve pittied thee, nor had compaſſion on thee; yet Chriſt beholding thy miſery, tooke pitty on thy eſtate, and ſpared not his owne life, but ſhed his precious blood to the death; yea, endured the wrath of his Father, and ſuffered vnut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7186:18"/> torments to procure thy peace:<note place="margin">Luc. 22.44.</note> his Agony was a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to teſtifie the terrour of his Soule; his ſweat like drops of blood trickling downe to the ground;<note place="margin">Mat. 27.29.</note> his bleſſed head crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thornes; his holy cheekes buffeted with fiſts; his backe whipped with ſcourges; his hands and feete nailed to the Croſſe, and his ſide pierced with a ſpeare, that the deareſt blood of his moſt precious heart guſhed out amaine: yea, his Paſſion ſo intolerable that he cryed out in the bitterneſſe of his ſoule, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.46.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And conſider, that all this did this bleſſed <hi>Lambe</hi> ſuffer to purchaſe thy peace. And if this will not moue thee,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 5.4, 5, 6.</note> adde thy owne vnthankefulneſſe, the abuſing of thoſe many and good graces, both ſpirituall and temporall which God hath giuen thee; the often crucifying of Chriſt againe by thy ſinnes, and grieuing the good Spirit, by whom thou art ſealed to the day of redemption. And if thy heart bee not more hard then Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants, certainly theſe meditations may breake it in peeces. But if all this doth not humble thee, then as before, thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> to prepare thy ſelfe for this exerciſe by <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>prayer,</hi> ſo leaue not off faſting and praying, and crying vnto God,<note place="margin">Ioel 2.12, 13.</note> till thy heart melt with ſorrow, and thy eies guſh out with riuers of waters. This oughteſt thou to doe for thine owne ſinnes, and for the ſinnes of the <hi>Time:</hi> And thus ſhalt thou be marked in the time of vengeance with the marke of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour:<note place="margin">Ezekiel 9.4.</note> and when the wicked ſhall periſh in the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, thou ſhalt haue peace.</p>
            <p>And to draw towards a concluſion of this; let nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thee from this <hi>examination,</hi> and <hi>humiliation</hi> of thy ſoule: But bee ſure to put it in practice, whoſoeuer thou art; or how great ſoeuer thy calling or occaſions bee: for the greater thou art, the more neede haſt thou of familiar acquaintance with God, of often conference with him in this kinde, for thy good, becauſe God is greater then all. Neglect it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whether thou be old or young, high or low, <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or <hi>Miniſter, noble</hi> or <hi>ignoble,</hi> rich or poore, man or woman, of what ſtate, or calling, or condition ſoeuer thou bee: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally forget it not then when thou art to draw neare vnto God,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7186:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> in receiuing of the holy and bleſſed Sacrament, the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the body and blood of Chriſt, for the worthy parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whereof,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28, 29</note> thou oughteſt to prepare thy ſelfe as thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt doe if thou wert that hower to die, and to paſſe either to heauen or hell, to eternall ioy, or eternall woe. Be ſure at that time therefore to put in practice this examination and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of thy ſoule, that vpon thy confeſſion and contrition thou maieſt haue abſolution at the hand of God, or of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, (if thou finde it needefull to procure thy peace.) Paſſe it not ouer ſleightly, but preſſe it to the full, till the good Spirit make thee to cry <hi>Abba father</hi> with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15, 16.</note> and witneſſe to thy ſpirit, that thou art the child of God; for by this the league of peace between thy God and conſcience ſhall bee renewed and preſerued. And Conſcience thus made quiet, is as a Caſtle of defence, or wall of braſſe vnto the Saints.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.12.</note> This made S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeake boldly, and in middeſt of miſeries reioyce in this the teſtimony of his conſcience.<note place="margin">Auguſtinus lib. cont. Secundin. Manichaeum Sentiasde Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtino quicquid libet, ſola in ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis dei conſcientia non accuſet.</note> This was a comfort vnto good S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by <hi>Secundinus,</hi> that he had forſaken Paganiſme and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Chriſt for hope of temporall preferment; I care not (ſaith the Father) what other men doe ſay, becauſe my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cleareth mee.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this moued the holy Martyres, moſt willingly to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe ſuch cruell deaths, and helliſh torments, and all for Chriſt; becauſe their Conſcience was to them a heauen of ioy, euen in a hell of griefe, of ſorrow. This is the benefit of a bleſſed Conſcience, which the Saints ſhall then receiue at full when as the Booke of Conſcience ſhall be opened.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Rules of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to get and preſerue a good Conſcience.</label> A word of Counſell before I end this Booke. To get and keepe a good and quiet Conſcience, take theſe rules with you for a guide to all the reſt. Since that your Conſcience is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and ſhall bee both a witneſſe and a iudge; Firſt labour rightly to informe your Conſcience, leſt blindneſſe lead your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience out of the way, and then ſhee erre in iudgment. And <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> next, ſince Conſcience is alwaies neare at hand, being placed of God within you, be ſure to aduiſe with Conſcience before you haue vndertaken any action. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt aske her counſell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7186:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> it be lawful which you intend to do or no: &amp; if your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doubt, then ſtay your heart, your tongue, your hand; nor thinke, nor ſpeake, nor doe before your Conſcience be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued. For as S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes, that what is not of faith is ſinne;<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23. <hi>In Roman.</hi>
               </note> ſo <hi>Origen, Fulgentius, Auguſtine, Chryſostome, Aquinas,</hi> with the Schooles, &amp; all the Current of our late Diuines conclude that caſe of Conſcience. Doe nothing doubting therefore; but if your conſcience once be quiet, then be you ſure to obey the checke of Conſcience, ſinne not againſt it, for he that ſins againſt his conſcience, loſeth the ſweete ſociety of a good, and getteth the trembling company of an euill conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The cloſe of this Booke.</label> Be alwaies guided therfore by a well informed conſcience, directed by the Law and Word of God; thus ſhall you ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy that bleſſed peace, euen when the Booke of Conſcience ſhall be opened.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The third Booke. The Booke of Life.</label> And thus you haue heard the ſecond Booke, the Booke of Conſcience. A word in briefe of the third and laſt.</p>
            <p>And this is <hi>Liber vitae,</hi> the Booke of Life: Of this Booke you may read in diuers places of the holy Scripture. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeakes of it to God. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. <hi>Dauid</hi> rehearſeth it: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.28. So doth the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> Chapter 4.3. and in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> it is remembred. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. Reioyce (ſaith our Sauiour) becauſe your names are written in heauen; <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.20. S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it the Booke of life, in which the names of the Saints are written, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3. So doth S. <hi>Iohn, Reuel.</hi> 3.5. And ſo it is named in my Text; <hi>And another Booke was opened, which is the Booke of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Explication.</label> By this Booke ſome vnderſtand Chriſt himſelfe, <note place="margin">Foelix Bidemba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius prompt. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equ. Claſſ. <hi>9.</hi> Them. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> in whom wee were choſen before the foundation of the world, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing predeſtinated vs vnto the adoption of children by Chriſt vnto himſelfe, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 5. And into whom (being wild Oliues by <hi>nature</hi>) wee are ingrafted by <hi>grace;</hi> and ſtand by <hi>faith, Rom.</hi> 11.17. and 19 verſes. And in whom the Saints Elect doe and ſhall abide, as the branches in the Vine. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.5. Chriſt dwelling in them and they in him. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.24. And in whom they ſhall bee found at the day of iudgement: for, <hi>At that day yee ſhall know,</hi> ſaith Chriſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7186:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>that I am in the Father, and you in mee, and I in you. Ioh.</hi> 14.20. And being found in Chriſt when the Bookes are opened, they ſhall certainly be ſaued: for that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is now and ſhall bee alwaies true; <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus. Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Perkinſus expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitione ſymboli. Zanchius de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro vitae.</note>Others vnderſtand this <hi>Booke</hi> not of Chriſt himſelfe, but of that Decree, and minde or purpoſe of God, in which hee hath ſet downe all thoſe, whom in and by Chriſt, according to the counſell of his owne will hee hath ordained to life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. that is, whom hee hath choſen to life and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If it be taken in eyther ſenſe: firſt, of Chriſt himſelfe, who is <hi>Arbor vitae,</hi> the Tree of life; and <hi>Liber exemplaris,</hi> a liuing exemplary Book; the characters of whoſe moſt vpright ſteps wee ſhould learne to imitate in all our actions; and who in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſome reſpect may well bee called <hi>The Booke of life.</hi> Or of that other <hi>Booke,</hi> the booke of <hi>Gods decree,</hi> which is truely and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the Booke of Life. It is true of both, that both theſe ſhall bee opened at that day of Aſſiſes; that which now is ſecret ſhall then bee ſhewed to all; it ſhall then bee knowne whoſe names are written in Chriſt; or whom God hath decreed to life eternall. All theſe Bookes ſhall be opened; the Booke of Gods <hi>preſcience,</hi> the Booke of mans <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Booke of life.</hi> And according to theſe Bookes, examination ſhall bee taken of the priſoners, and euidence giuen vnto the Iudge; and as this is giuen ſo ſhall the ſentence bee declared.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> O happie, thrice happie then ſhall that man bee, in the Booke of whoſe conſcience ſhall bee found thoſe <hi>characters</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> which may agree to thoſe are written in the Booke of Life: For as in time of Grace, there is no man truly giueth his name to Chriſt, or reliſheth aright his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, but they whoſe names are written in the Booke of Life: So in that time of iudgment there is none ſhall be found writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in that <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> but thoſe who in the time of mercy haue had within their hearts and conſciences imprinted, as in a Booke,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6. Heb. 12 14.</note> thoſe <hi>golden letters</hi> both of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>holineſſe</hi> at leſt in ſuch a meaſure as God in Chriſt hath promiſed to accept,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7186:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> For as of old in the returne from the captiuity of Babylon, thoſe Iewes, who could not find the writing of their Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, and ſhew their Fathers houſe, were put from all their Offices as vncleane, and might not bee in number of the Prieſts: <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 7.64. So in that Generall returne from the <hi>Captiuity</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Babylon</hi> of this world,<note place="margin">Brightmannus in Apocalypſ.</note> thoſe only ſhall haue places in the Church Tryumphant, and liue as Kings and Prieſts with Chriſt, who can bring forth this written <hi>Booke,</hi> (the Booke of Faith and Holineſſe in their hearts and conſciences) as a true Copie or Counterpane of that Booke of Life, and proue themſelues by <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe</hi> to bee the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> For as God hath elected vs to <hi>Happineſſe</hi> in the Kingdome of glory, which is the end at which we ayme, and which wee endeuour to obtaine; ſo hath he choſen vs to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe</hi> (which are the meanes to bring vnto that end,) as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> And therefore woe and miſery ſhall bee vnto the wicked, whoſe <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not faire and white like to the Saints, made glorious with the engrauen forme of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (imputed and inhaerent:) But foule and blacke, in which they dayly write enormous crimes, and euery moment ſpot their Soules with foule impieties. So that there is no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with their <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and therefore (without true repentance while the Sun doth ſhine, and day of Grace doth laſt) in ſtead of Life, &amp; Heauen of ioy, a Death, and Hell of woe, ſhall be their portion.</p>
            <p>O then beloued,<note place="margin">Application. Origen, Hom. <hi>5.</hi> in Leuit.</note> if (as <hi>Origen</hi> obſerues) when a cauſe is to bee pleaded before an earthly Iudge, which concerneth a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Land, vpon the leaſt feare or doubt, a man will bee ſo carefull and watch ſo diligently, that all things may bee in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe: his witneſſe prepared, his Counſell informed, that the beſt of his cauſe may be opened, and (if it bee poſſible) the Iudge before-hand poſſeſſed, that the right is on his ſide, though it be (as often it proues to be) on the contrary.</p>
            <p>How much more carefull ſhould euery Chriſtian bee, to prepare himſelfe, that hee may bee in a readineſſe before that tribunall <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when his title to heauen it ſelfe ſhall be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7186:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> called in queſtion; and except his euidence be good, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance firme in the law of faith, he ſhall loſe not a Cottage, but a Kingdome, the Kingdome of Heauen, (that light and life of glory) and be caſt into vtter darkeneſſe, where ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth: <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.30.</p>
            <p>It deepely concerneth euery Chriſtian therefore to haue a care of this in all their actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, eſpecially thoſe men vnto whoſe care and conſcience is committed the execution of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Iudgment.</hi> Becauſe ſuch are publike perſons, and at that day of <hi>Aſſiſes</hi> when the Iudgement Seate is ſet, and the Bookes are opened: <hi>Daniel</hi> 7.10. They ſhall giue account vnto God both for their owne ſoules, and the ſoules of others (of all thoſe whom God at any time hath deliuered to their charge) for looke what good hath followed by their care and faithfulneſſe in their ſeuerall places; they ſhall not loſe their reward: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of glory ſhall be giuen them. And looke what euill ſhall enſue, by their negligence or vnfaithfull dealing, they ſhall not loſe their reward; the reward of ſhame &amp; confuſion ſhall be their portion: For the bookes ſhall opened, and God will render to euery one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> according to their workes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A particular Exhortation &amp; Application to the Auditory.</label> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Bellarm. deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi>
               </note>One word therefore of <hi>Exhortation</hi> to you my <hi>Auditors</hi> in particular, who (by Gods prouidence) at this time are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the execution of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and I haue done.</p>
            <p>It was decreed in that firſt generall <hi>Councell</hi> holden at <hi>Nice,</hi> about the yeare of our Lord three hundred and thirty, in which, that wicked Hereſie of <hi>Arius,</hi> was condemned by the conſent of three hundred and eighteene Fathers, (as Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Hiſtories relate) That to preuent the dangers which delay might bring to the Church, there ſhould be twice euery yeere a <hi>Prouinciall Synod,</hi> or <hi>Councell,</hi> of the Biſhops, in which they ſhould examine all caſes of Controuerſie, and end them to procure peace of the Church; the firſt of theſe Councels was held, <hi>Ante dies Quadrageſimae,</hi> before the time of Lent, and the Second <hi>Circa tempus Autumni</hi> about the time of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne (as it is expreſſed in the firſt <hi>Canon</hi> of that <hi>Nicen</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.)</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7186:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And the like commendable cuſtome hath long ſince beene inſtituted in this Kingdome for temporall gouernment in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, that wiſe and learned Prince, (as ſome writers affirme) ſince whom <hi>Itinerary Iudges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boterus.</note> (like <hi>Samuel</hi> that patterne of Iuſtice) haue had both their <hi>Circuit</hi> and <hi>Center.</hi> For as <hi>Samuel</hi> went from yeare to yeare in <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit</hi> to <hi>Bethel,</hi> and <hi>Gilgal,</hi> and <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> and iudged <hi>Iſrael</hi> in all thoſe places; and returned to <hi>Ramah</hi> (that <hi>Center</hi> of Iuſtice) where he iudged <hi>Iſrael</hi> againe, and built an Altar vnto the Lord, (as you may read) 1. <hi>Samuel.</hi> 7.17.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Weſtminſter the Center of Iuſtice.</label> So is it alſo with vs, (bleſſed be God for it) vnder our <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Moſes,</hi> (whoſe peace and proſperity God long continue amongſt vs, and let our hearts anſwer, Amen, Amen.) we haue our learned and religious <hi>Samuels,</hi> our iuſt and righteous <hi>Iudges,</hi> which (for our vnſpeakeable benefit) come home vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, into euery <hi>Shire</hi> and corner of the Land; executing Iuſtice and Iudgement, for the maintenance of vertue, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of vice. And in that <hi>Common place</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> whither they returne as to their Center, at Termes appointed ſitting on Thrones of Iuſtice, and weighing each mans Cauſe with an equall ballance, both in <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed may be deliuered, and wrong dealers puniſhed. Theſe (like <hi>Conſcience</hi>) are <hi>Demi-Gods</hi> on <hi>earth:</hi> (I ſay ye are Gods, ſaith the Pſalmiſt) to whom is appointed from God and our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King, this high and honorable office,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> for the glory of God, and good of the Kingdome. And for whom, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth, <hi>Supplications, and prayers, and interceſſions, and giuing of thankes is to be made, that we may lead a quiet and a peaceable life,</hi> in all godlineſſe and <hi>honeſty,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak in particular therefore to you my honorable Lords, I muſt ſay as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſometimes ſaid to his Auditors, <hi>Non eſt mea humilitatis dictare vobis:</hi> It is not for my humility to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate vnto you, or tell you what you ſhould doe: I know you are wiſe, you are learned, you are religious, the booke of your Conſcience is already opened: and therefore <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, law</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> will be your guide in all things. And for this I will pray, that caſting your eyes vpon this viſion, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7186:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> viewing euery part of it at your leaſures,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ad monach. In Chriſti Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio ſine accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione perſonaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſine ambitu po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatum, aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter iudicabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Domini &amp; ſerui, diuites &amp; pauperes. Plutarch. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis illuſtr. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione Numa &amp; Lycurgi. Magiſter Sent. lib. <hi>2.</hi> diſtinct. <hi>26.</hi> Aquinas prim. ſecund. qu. <hi>109.</hi> art. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> you may take the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt to be your patterne; that auoiding thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous flatterers, (friends in ſhew, but enemies in ſubſtance) that is, <hi>loue</hi> or <hi>hatred, feare</hi> or <hi>couetouſneſſe</hi> (by which iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is often peruerted) you may be endued with <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Fortitude,</hi> (like <hi>Numa</hi> and <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> thoſe two famous Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours) and being armed with vertue as with an inuincible ſhield, keepe the Caſtle of a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> inuiolable. Thus ſhall ye find that peace of Conſcience (that moſt happy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of a righteous man) euen when the booke of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall bee opened.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Enchiridon, Chapter the thirty two, the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Sentences, Aquinas,</hi> and the Schoole men vpon them, obſerue a twofold grace of God neceſſary for a Chriſtian: the firſt is <hi>Gratia praeueniens,</hi> a preuenting grace, to prepare our wils and hearts to workes of pietie. The ſecond is <hi>Gratia ſubſequens,</hi> a ſubſequent grace, to aſſiſt and helpe vs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in well doing. And in like manner there is a twofold Iuſtice neceſſary for the well gouerning of a Common-wealth; the firſt is <hi>Iuſtitia praeueniens,</hi> a preuenting Iuſtice, to encourage to vertue, and by timely puniſhments to keepe from greater miſchiefes: The ſecond is <hi>Iuſtitia puniens,</hi> puniſhing iuſtice, to cut downe vice with extremity, when the wound is growne incurable.<note place="margin">Pſal. 201.1.</note> The firſt is <hi>mercy,</hi> the ſecond <hi>iudgement:</hi> The firſt hath place in criminall, the ſecond in capitall offences. Of the firſt many a one may ſay, and that truly; <hi>Periiſſem niſi periiſſem,</hi> I had periſhed, vnleſſe I had periſhed; if I had not beene pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for <hi>idleneſſe, drunkenneſſe,</hi> or <hi>prophaneneſſe,</hi> I had beene puniſhed for <hi>theft,</hi> or <hi>murder,</hi> or worſe <hi>impieties.</hi> And of the ſecond many a one hath ſaid (and that as truly) <hi>Si periiſſem, non periiſſem;</hi> If I had beene puniſhed by my <hi>parents</hi> or <hi>gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> or <hi>magiſtrats,</hi> for leſſer faults, I had not now been puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this ſhamefull death, for ſo foule and horrible a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: (this you may often heare if you bee preſent at the execution of ſuch Malefactors.) So that as many a man doth ſuffer death for his owne offences; ſo is many a man hanged, for the negligence of his Parents, or Maſters, or Gouernours,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7186:22"/> who ſhould by timely puniſhments haue preuented ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>Thankes</hi> bee to God we haue many worthy <hi>Iudges</hi> in this Kingdome, who are carefull, and zealous for the execution both of the one and other Iuſtice. But the care of them is not ſufficient, without the helpe and aſſiſtance of others: For though they be <hi>Gods,</hi> yet are they not <hi>Omniſcient,</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee all offences, nor know all offenders. There bee many ſinnes which cry for <hi>Vengeance,</hi> and yet the cry of them is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtopped before it commeth to their <hi>Eares,</hi> or elſe the ſins themſelues (like painted Harlots) are ſo guilded ouer with colours of deceit, that their vgly countenances cannot bee ſeene, and by this meanes they eſcape vnpuniſhed. I muſt now therefore turne my ſpeech vnto you who are <hi>Aſsiſtants</hi> and <hi>Helpers</hi> in the Execution of Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>And for ſuch who are of a <hi>Higher Order</hi> appoynted as <hi>Iudges</hi> in priuate <hi>Seſſions</hi> for puniſhment of leſſer offences, and to binde ouer the reſt to the Examination and Tryall of this <hi>Greater Aſſiſes:</hi> I may ſpeake it with <hi>Ioy,</hi> for the Honour and credit of this <hi>Countrey,</hi> (In which I am yet but a ſtranger) I know ſome, and I haue heard of many <hi>Honorable, Worſhipfull, Learned,</hi> and <hi>Religious Iuſtices;</hi> whoſe care and Conſcience is dayly publiſhed in their ſeuerall Circuits by their ſeuerall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. (And I pray God yee may goe on in ſincerity of ſoule and Conſcience; knowing for certaine, yee ſhall not loſe your reward, when the Bookes ſhall bee opened, and that day of Refreſhing ſhall come.<note place="margin">Acts 3.19.</note>)</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, for Inferiour Officers, who are either to informe the Court by their Preſentments according to Oath and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles giuen in charge, or elſe to proſecute and ſee Iuſtice execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when information and ſentence is giuen: I doubt not but amongſt theſe alſo there are many <hi>honeſt, religious</hi> and conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men, who will doe their beſt both for preuenting and puniſhing Iuſtice. But if all bee ſuch, what meaneth then this bleating of the <hi>Sheepe,</hi> &amp; lowing of the <hi>Oxen,</hi> &amp; voyce of King <hi>Agag,</hi> which ſtill ſound in our eares? (as <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Saul,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.14.) whence is there ſo many impieties that ſtill lurke in <hi>Corners</hi> oftentimes daring to <hi>Out-face</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> and in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7186:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpite of reprehenſion continue amongſt vs?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Similitude.</label> This ſheweth plaine, that as there is <hi>Iuſtitia</hi> the free courſe of Iuſtice, amongſt ſuch who are friends of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity:</hi> ſo there is <hi>Iuſtitiam,</hi> a ſtay and ſtoppe of the Current of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> amongſt thoſe who for feare, or affection, or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Wiliel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood de purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Canonica.</note> ſpare to puniſh impiety. There is a rule in the <hi>Canon</hi> Law, that if a man bee <hi>Defamed, apud bonos, &amp; graues,</hi> amongſt good, and graue men (being preſented to the Ordinary) hee may be enioyned his purgation, <hi>Cum Sexta manu honeſtorum virorum:</hi> with ſix of his honeſt Neighbours, and if hee faile in this, be put to his <hi>Penance.</hi> It it much to bee feared that if ſome inferiour <hi>Officers</hi> were put to this <hi>Tryall,</hi> they would faile in purgation, and for their <hi>Periury</hi> haue <hi>Penance</hi> enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them. And happie were they if this might waſh out the blots of their Conſciences; yea ſeuen yeares penance (as was long ſince decreed in the Ancient <hi>Canons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Canon. Fabian.</note> for ſuch kinde of Offenders.) But woe bee to that ſoule whoſe Conſcience is ſpotted with that ſoule impurity. The ſtay of Iuſtice is like the ſtay of a current, or running ſtreame, it will on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ouerflow the bankes; and if it haue not paſſage, ſpoyle a whole Countrey. It were farre better that one rotten mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhould be cut off from the body, then the whole body pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: and much more profitable that one corrupt Officer ſhould be ſeuerely puniſhed, then that <hi>Execution,</hi> which is the <hi>Life of Law,</hi> ſhould be put to death. I haue heard of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in ſome Countryes remote, that when the <hi>Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens</hi> haue preſented offenders, they haue beene called to the Court, and paying their Fees, the <hi>Chancellors,</hi> or <hi>Officials,</hi> or their <hi>Deputies,</hi> or <hi>Surrogates,</hi> haue preſently diſmiſſed them, and ſo the buſineſſe ended; no <hi>reformation,</hi> no <hi>penance</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned, no ſatisfaction to the Congregation.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Conſtables</hi> and inferiour <hi>Officers</hi> haue complained as much of <hi>Temporall proceedings.</hi> But I hope there is no ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint can iuſtly be taken vp in theſe parts of the world. <hi>Omnia venalia Romae,</hi> Al things are vendible at <hi>Rome:</hi> but for <hi>Bribery</hi> &amp; <hi>Periury,</hi> let them not be heard of in our Land; for both are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable, and <hi>Periury</hi> aboue all is a crying wickedneſſe.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:7186:23"/>
            <p>I haue read of an excellent law amongſt the Turkes, that, <hi>If any man did ſweare, his tongue ſhould bee ſhaued and waſhed in vineger.</hi> If all falſe ſwearers amongſt Chriſtians had receiued this puniſhment, wee ſhould not heare a complaint of ſo many <hi>knaues</hi> of the <hi>poſt,</hi> who are not aſhamed to ſay one to another, <hi>Lend my friend an oath this Aſſiſes, and I will lend thy friend an oath the next.</hi> A fearefull ſaying; for while they lend an <hi>oath</hi> to their friend, they forfeit their <hi>ſoules</hi> to the <hi>Deuill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>A watchword to the Iurymen</label> Take heed of this all you who are called to giue in euidence, or who are empannelled on any Iury, either for tryal of rights, or of life and death, which is moſt dangerous; let not feare nor fauour draw you from iuſtice, but ſtand out boldly with courage in a rightfull cauſe. Sinne not againſt your <hi>Conſcience;</hi> for though the Papiſts may tell you,<note place="margin">M. Parſons Reckon. cap. 4. Sect. 11. Pag. 265. &amp; pag. 64. <hi>Bulla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ii Quin.</hi> confirmed by <hi>Greg.</hi> 13 againſt Qu. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Aequiuocation</hi> is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; or the Ieſuits preach, that the <hi>Pope</hi> can abſolue from an Oath; (yea, the Oath of Alleageance, that a <hi>Subiect</hi> may take armes againſt his <hi>Prince,</hi> or by treaſon murther a Magiſtrate who is not of their Religion) yet Chriſt Ieſus taught no ſuch doctrine, nor his Apoſtles, nor the ancient Fathers of the Church; nor doth the Church of England approue it. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not your ſelues therefore, but informe your conſciences aright, and giue euidence thereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Concluſion.</label> And to conclude all; <note place="margin">Zech. 5.2, 3, 4.</note> Read at your leaſures that fift Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Prophecy of <hi>Zechary,</hi> the ſecond, third, and fourth Verſes: And thinke on that fearefull <hi>curſe</hi> which ſhall remaine in the <hi>houſe of the falſe ſwearer, and conſume it with the timber and ſtones thereof.</hi> And remember this viſion (a part of which is my Text) that as certainly as there is now a <hi>particular Aſſiſes,</hi> wherein you are now to giue <hi>euidence</hi> or <hi>verdict,</hi> and to aſſiſt in the iudgment of others; ſo the time ſhall come, when there ſhall bee a <hi>generall Aſſiſes,</hi> wherein Chriſt Ieſus, that Prince of righteouſneſſe, ſhall be the <hi>Iudge;</hi> wherein you your ſelues ſhall bee the Priſoners (for none are excepted;) wherein the Bookes ſhall bee opened; the <hi>Booke</hi> of Gods <hi>preſcience,</hi> the <hi>Booke</hi> of euery mans particular <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi> And the <hi>Dead</hi> both ſmall and great, yea both dead and liuing; euery man, and euery woman that are, or haue beene,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7186:24"/> or ſhall be hereafter in the world, they ſhall all ſtand before God, and bee iudged of thoſe things which are written in the Bookes according to their workes. In the <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>God</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labour earneſtly to get and preſerue a good Conſcience in all your actions, and pray with feruency for the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of Gods gracious <hi>Spirit;</hi> and my prayer ſhall be the ſame for you all, which S. <hi>Pauls</hi> once was for his Chriſtian Theſſalonians; <hi>That the very God of peace will ſanctifie you throughout;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>and I pray God, that your whole ſpirit and ſoule and body may bee preſerued blameleſſe vnto that comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> To whom with the Father and the bleſſed Spirit bee aſcribed all honour, and power, and glory; all might, and maieſty, and dominion, now and for euer. AMEN.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed are all they who remember that laſt, great, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſiſes, when thoſe <hi>Bookes</hi> ſhall bee opened; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to get and preſerue a good, a pure, and a peaceable Conſcience in all their thoughts, words, and workes.</p>
            <p>The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the loue of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the ſweet and comfortable fellowſhip of God the Holy Spirit bee with vs, bleſſe, preſerue and keepe vs, and euery one of his Saints and Seruants, both in bodies, in ſoules, in eſtates and good names, from all dangers, and from all our enemies, both ſpirituall and temporall, the reſt of this day, and for euermore. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>Gloria Trin-uni Deo.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7186:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
